<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain and evident discovery of the two personal comings of Christ one at the beginning of his thousand years reign, Rev. 20, 4, with his holy and blessed raised saints in the Now [sic] Jerusalem, come down from God out of heaven, Rev. 21, the other after the little space when the thousand years are ended, &amp;c. : whereunto are added many profitable applications of the same doctrine for all sorts of persons.</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59938</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38237</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17215769</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17215769</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106268</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59938)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106268)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1100:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain and evident discovery of the two personal comings of Christ one at the beginning of his thousand years reign, Rev. 20, 4, with his holy and blessed raised saints in the Now [sic] Jerusalem, come down from God out of heaven, Rev. 21, the other after the little space when the thousand years are ended, &amp;c. : whereunto are added many profitable applications of the same doctrine for all sorts of persons.</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 51.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XX-XXI --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106268:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106268:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A plain and evident Diſcovery of the two Perſonal Comings of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> one at the beginning of his Thouſand years Reign, <hi>Rev. 20.4.</hi> with his holy and bleſſed raiſed Saints in the Now Jeruſalem, come down from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev. 21.</hi> the other after the little ſpace when the Thouſand years are ended, &amp;c. Whereunto are added, many profitable Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of the ſame Doctrine for all ſorts of perſons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 22.20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Surely I come quickly: Amen. Even ſo, come Lord Jeſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words contain Chriſt's moſt certain Aſſeveration of his ſecond Perſonal Coming, whereunto is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed the Spirits and Brides aſſent &amp; conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and their aſſured expectation thereof in its time and due order: They are the laſt words of holy Scripture (ſaving a uſual Salutation) and therefore like to be words of great conſequence, and that if we conſider how and by whom ſpoken, and how and by whom enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and improved, as in the latter part; but we ſhall not here inſiſt on them, as to handle them as a Text, ſave only as they hold out to us the great Perſonal Appearance of the Coming of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8.</note> now ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approaching, which the world in great part (as it is likely) will not believe, till they in great part feel the terror of it: when at the ſaid Appearance and his Kingdom he will begin to judge both quick and dead, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. as in the ſequel we doubt not will, by the aſſiſtance and guidance of God's Spirit and Truth, be made to right enquirers e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently to appear.</p>
            <p>In chap. 1.7. it was proclaimed with an <hi>Ecce,</hi> a note of obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>(Behold)</hi> aforehand for the Churches great conſolation before her troubles began, that even then her Deliverer had begun his journey (as it were) for her help and deliverance: <hi>Behold, he cometh with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo that pierced him:</hi> but alſo for the wo and miſery of the wicked world likewiſe, for <hi>all Nations ſhall wail becauſe of him;</hi> and both theſe aſcertained, with <hi>Even ſo, Amen:</hi> to ſhew that his coming in the clouds of Heaven, in ſuch a glorious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106268:2"/>as the holy Scriptures abundantly ſhew, or <hi>with clouds,</hi> (as here) ſhall be moſt certain and infallible, and of great concernment for his faithful People to obſerve all along, to remember, conſider, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove through all the orders of times in this moſt ſacred Prophetical Book: But now at the latter end when he comes to ſet home this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in its due order of accompliſhment, as foreſeeing what hindrances in that reſpect his People would find in the latter dayes, he then ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hard and often upon this ſtring, to rouſe them, and awaken that Faith that then would be hard to be found: <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8. ſaith he in his own perſon three times in this 22th chapter: firſt, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Behold, I come quickly:</hi> again, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>And behold, I come quickly:</hi> and laſtly in this 20th verſ. <hi>Surely I come quickly:</hi> ſtill in each verſe encouraging his People to wait for his coming that would make amends for all, and that in the worſt times before his coming, which would then ſhortly be, when the laſt head of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monſter was to fall in its order into utter perdition in the <hi>Armageddon</hi> battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.14, 16, 17. and fully executed, chap. 19.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he ſhould moſt certainly then ſo come to ſet up his glorious Kingdom on Earth, and then to have his reward with him for all ſorts, <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. that ſo, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>all that ſuffer with him</hi> in his Kingdom of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>may reign with him</hi> in his Kingdom of Power, as their Meſſiah and Deliverer on Earth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. <hi>That they may ſerve him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fear</hi> (there) <hi>in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the dayes of their lives, Luke</hi> 1.74. So by theſe and the like means the Bride, the Lamb's Wife, the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, then ſhortly to be made perfect in one, (as, <hi>John</hi> 17. our Saviour prayed on Earth at his firſt-coming, for his Saints happineſs on Earth at his ſecond coming) ſhould, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the due order of things ſet down in this moſt divine Book, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it in the end of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, and when his own glorious Kingdom, as Mediator, ſhould ſucceed on Earth, and become that Mountain filling the whole Earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. of which he ſets down in the four laſt chapters: Firſt, the removal of the hinderers, the Pope and his adherents, chap. 19. and then of the Devil and his angels, chap. 20.1, 2, 3. Secondly, the erecting of his excellent Dominion; firſt, by the Brides making ready, when ſhe ſhould ſo ſing her <hi>Alleluja's</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her Enemies ruine, in the old mother-tongue, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4, 5. and alſo the Saints be raiſed in order; firſt, ſuch as were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and then, &amp;c. chap. 20.4. and more fully, chap. 11.18. who muſt then have Judgment given to them, that is, power of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Thrones, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. and this for a thouſand years; and having ſhewed what Satan with the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> chap. 20.7,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106268:2"/>8, 9, 10. ſhould attempt for a little ſpace, till both be ſent to Hell; and in what way and manner he will thereupon begin the laſt Seſſion of Judgment, from ver. 10. to the end: he then in the two laſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters decyphers the excellent bleſſed and holy ſtate of his own and his Saints Kingdom upon Earth, with their priviledges and advantages therein, as may abundantly appear from chap. 21 &amp; 22: wherein from the conſideration of this his own next Perſonal Coming he ſtirs up all his People to come to him, to be fit to welcome his Coming, <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>The Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come: and let him that heareth</hi> (ſpiritually) <hi>come; and let him that is athirſt, come, &amp;c.</hi> that when they hear him ſay, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>Surely I come quickly,</hi> they may by faith, and with fervent deſires (as his Bride) ſay, <hi>Amen. Even ſo, come Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all theſe warnings, with frequent aſſertings of theſe things, which he ſets down in theſe four laſt chapters of this Book: as chap. 19.7, 8. <hi>Theſe are the true ſayings of God.</hi> &amp; ch. 21.5. <hi>Theſe words are true and faithful:</hi> chap. 22.6. <hi>Theſe ſayings are faithful and true;</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 10. forbids this Book to be ſealed, <hi>becauſe the time is at hand,</hi> viz. in the order of the accompliſhment of all contained in this Book: and in this 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſ. concludes with his own moſt ſure teſtimony: <hi>He which teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, Surely I come quickly, &amp;c.</hi> All which he ſeems to do as knowing how the faith of theſe things would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the world about the time he ſhould ſo come in the clouds, or with clouds, as chap. 1.7. even this coming of which he ſaith, <hi>Surely I come quickly.</hi> And as we now find by experience at this very time, as reſpecting his ſpecial ſpiritual powerful coming, ſo much ſlighted and oppoſed by moſt of men; and his next perſonal coming is not like to be leſs ſlighted and mocked at, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. but by the Scoffers of thoſe times very poſſible much more.</p>
            <p>Now whereas beſides Chriſt's coming in humility to take our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to ſuffer for his Church, there remains according to holy Scripture (as we hope (by the Grace of God) to make manifeſt to all impartial ſearchers into theſe Myſteries) there ſtill remains a twofold perſonal coming of Chriſt: One when God will ſubdue and deſtroy the great Enemies of Chriſt and his People, both <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> namely the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> ſet forth by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> under the titles of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> chap. 38 &amp; 39. before he ſet up his <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> chap. 40 to the end of the Book, <hi>Whoſe name ſhall be JEHOVAH SHAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MA, the Lord is there:</hi> juſt as the Beaſt and his Armies ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, &amp;c. before the <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Rev. 19, &amp; 20, &amp; 21. called <hi>the Holy, Beloved, the great and holy Jeruſalem,</hi> which is alſo there <hi>the Bride, the Lambs Wife,</hi> be built by God's own hand; as <hi>Heb.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106268:3"/>11. which will be accompliſhed at the ſounding of the ſeventh Angel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.16. upon which comes in the thouſand years when Chriſt will take to himſelf his great Power, and reign, as chap. 19. <hi>v.</hi> 1 to <hi>v.</hi> 10. And afterwards when our bleſſed Saviour had given a clear and perfect computation of all ſucceeding times to the end of the world, with all the ſuiting circumſtances before, in, at the end, and after his ſaid thouſand years Reign on Earth: in that laſt Table of the laſt and beſt times in the new World in chap. 20. (as he gave a Table of all the laſt and worſt times, chap. 11. to ver. 16. in the old bad World) he ſhews manifeſtly from the compleating of that Judgment upon thoſe great Enemies from his ſecond Perſonal Apearance or Coming at that time, when the Judgment was ſet to deſtroy the Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10. there are to paſs above a thouſand years before the third, when is to be the laſt Seſſion of the day of Judgment at the general Reſurrection of all that lived not again before, both good and bad, as our Saviour diſtinctly teacheth, chap. 20. called there <hi>the reſt of the dead that lived not again before,</hi> ver. 5. ſetting forth to the end, the manner of God's carrying<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many wonderful works from thence unto the end. And then Chriſt further proceeds in the two laſt chapters, to ſet forth in a very divine and wonderful manner the ſucceeding glorious eſtate of his Church upon Earth, with her excellent prerogatives and priviledges all that time of his thouſand years Reign, from his ſecond coming to his third, ſaving the little ſpace Satan is after looſed and ſeduceth the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> chap. 20.7, 8, 9, 10. to their deſtruction; to which enſueth the laſt Judgment, ver. 11. to the end: when he will again deſcend from Heaven, not with clouds, as at his ſecond coming, but with a ſhout and the voice of an Arch-Angel, and the Trump of God, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as here, chap. 20.11. ſitting upon a great white Throne, before whoſe face Heaven and Earth fled away.</p>
            <p>Now to that end we may the better and more clearly carry on this great work to ſatisfaction of ſome, hitherto unreſolved conſciencious Chriſtians, we ſhall endeavour to this purpoſe to ſet down many evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Texts of holy Scriptures, upon the advantage of what hath been already ſaid, which may appear manifeſtly to relate to thoſe two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Comings: and then come more fully to conſider them from the order of their diſtinct times wherein they are to be, both from <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions and the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> in both which we have the ſeries and order of the accompliſhment of the Generalities of the greateſt marters, wherein God's glory and the Churches concernment ſhould lie, from the beginning of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions for the ſpace of above three
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106268:3"/>thouſand three hundred years. 2dly, To obſerve, for Chriſtians infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the different names and titles ſometimes given to them, and anſwerably thereunto their natures as ſuitable to thoſe names. 3dly, The different things to be done by Chriſt at both thoſe ſaid Comings, with many diſtinct particularities under both thoſe heads, beſides what is orderly to be accompliſhed both according to <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, the faithful and true Witneſs, from his ſecond to his third perſonal coming at the laſt reſurrection of good and bad, which our Saviour after his aſcenſion into Heaven hath at laſt declared and opened, and left unſealed (as was noted) for his Churches inſtruction and comfort, as by ſpecial order is manifeſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.10. by which means his People are inabled rightly to underſtand many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe dark paſſages of Old and New Teſtament, and beſides hath given great incouragement of bleſſing to the faithfull and diligent ſearching into them, to the ſpiritual hearing or believing of them, and to the keeping of the ſayings of that Book, chap. 1.3.</p>
            <p>Now therefore in reference to the firſt part of our buſineſs let it be obſerved, That many judicious men, well vers'd in the myſteries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the latter times, unanimouſly agree that Chriſt will remain, from his appearance or coming at the deſtruction of Aptichriſt, thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward all the thouſand years of his reigning with his raiſed Saints in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and will (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> conceives probably) through that time be raiſing up all the dead bodies of all the former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceaſed Saints, to the end of that thouſand years, in their own or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, having departed out of this life during the Kingdom of the Stone, or the Kingdom of Patience, for almoſt ſeventeen hundred years, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving believed through their word (as is ſaid <hi>John</hi> 17.) namely by the Apoſtles Doctrine, with all the Faithful under the Old Teſtament, even till that time when they ſhall all be made perfect in one with Chriſt their viſible Head, then in that his glorious Kingdom on Earth for the ſaid thouſand years ſpace, unto which that Scripture muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be referred, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. from ver. 19 to 25. But it ſeems from the time that Satan, at the end of the thouſand years, ſhall be looſed for a little ſeaſon, that Chriſt will withdraw from the world for that little ſeaſon, to give (as it were) opportunity to the Devil to play his laſt moſt abominable wicked prank in the world with his ſeduced Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> as followeth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7, 8, 9. to bring on that laſt deſtruction of all them, and the whole World, v. 10. which thereupon will ſuddenly be diſſolved, as follows, ver. 11 to the end; when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plainly ſaith, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Chriſt will again deſcend from Heaven with a ſhout, with the voice of the Arch-Angel,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106268:4"/>and with the Trump of God;</hi> and ſhews that immediately the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt, (namely ſuch as had died in the thouſand years ſince his ſecond coming) that they with ſuch as are alive and remain all the time ſince they were raiſed to live again upon Earth, (which he ſpeaks of twice, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 17.) as being in a very different condition from thoſe that are dead then, and in the thouſand years, and to be firſt raiſed when all wicked men are to be raiſed. Where note, he ſaith not, <hi>We ſhall riſe firſt</hi> then, as he did of the other ſtate, <hi>we that are alive and remain;</hi> but, <hi>the dead in Chriſt;</hi> and that they, with all ſuch as were in the natural life on Earth, who ſhould have a momentany change then inſtead of a death; and alſo that all thoſe that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore raiſed in the thouſand years, ſhould all at once be rapt up to meet Chriſt in the air, and altogether be thenceforth ever with the Lord; who had for a little time before abſented himſelf from them. And that the Apoſtle in this Epiſtle ſpeaks both of his ſecond and third coming, may thus further be made to appear, chap. 3.13. he ſpeaks of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt with <hi>All</hi> his Saints; and again, chap. 4.14. he ſaith alſo, <hi>them alſo that ſleep in Jeſus ſhall God bring with him:</hi> he brings them with him at his next appearance to take their bodies in the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. but at his third coming they are not ſaid to be brought with him, but <hi>rapt up to meet him in the air,</hi> when he is deſcended from Heaven: Before he had left them a little ſeaſon, but afterwards they ſhall be <hi>ever with the Lord.</hi> To which purpoſe <hi>Enoch</hi> propheſied of old of his firſt coming, <hi>Jude</hi> 14.8. <hi>Behold, the Lord cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints:</hi> that is, when the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> which is above, and called by the Apoſtle, <hi>The Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all,</hi> Gal. 4.26. ſhall come down from God out of Heaven at his ſecond coming at the time of the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.20, 21. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. being prepared as a Bride adorned for her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: when he will make all things new, and the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with men, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 5. when the ſouls beheaded for the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Jeſus ſhall live and reign with Chriſt the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and when he will begin that judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. to reward his ſervants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his Name both ſmall and great: and when the four Beaſts (or rather living wights) and the twenty four Elders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. ſhall actually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that which they foreſaw in Viſion above one thouſand five hundred years before that they ſhould reign upon earth; for he is not ſaid to bring them with him at his third coming, but to take them up to him to meet him in the air, by a ſudden reſurrection, and momentany change and rapture, who before in great part lived again, and remained
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106268:4"/>upon Earth, or in the World, until that time; and yet he ſaith that they ſhould not prevent thoſe that were then aſleep: and alſo ſhews, that though Chriſt had left them for a ſeaſon before, yet from thence-for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward they ſhould <hi>all ever be with the Lord.</hi> And for his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture is very full and clear, at the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, from <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. when he ſhall come in the cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of Heaven; and <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold, he cometh with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him:</hi> and 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. he will then deſtroy the Man of Sin with the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his Coming, when he ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, taking vengeance on thoſe wicked men who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his Power; and then alſo be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his Saints, and admired in all them that believe, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. And this is his appearance at his Kingdom, when he will judge both quick &amp; dead, as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. by deſtroying wicked men, and rewarding the Righteous, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. &amp; 20.4. for then God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to make his foes his footſtool, when having taken to himſelf his great Power, he deſtroyes them that deſtroyed the Earth, as follows in <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and all this will be at or about the ſame time, when <hi>Michael</hi> the great Prince (that is, the Meſſiah) ſhall ſtand up to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his People, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. when ſuch a time of trouble will be as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was ſince there was a Nation: and ſuch a great Earthquake alſo will be then at the pouring-out of the laſt Viol to finiſh the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Beaſt, as never was ſince men were upon the Earth even till that time, ſo mighty an Earthquake and ſo great, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. latter end, and likewiſe <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. &amp; ver. 26. for the Judgment is ſet to that end, and the Books then opened, as in ver. 10. See many Texts that ſpeak of this his ſecond coming in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 42, 43, 44. and for his perſonal appearance, which is the ſame ſecond coming in the <hi>Forerunner,</hi> p. 47, 48. And for his third deſcending with a ſhout from heaven, and the voyce of the Archangel, and the Trump of God, when the reſt of the Saints that dyed in the thouſand years ſhall be again raiſed, as the other were in the thouſand years that had reigned with Chriſt before upon earth, before Satan ſeduced the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Abridgm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> there is above a thouſand years ſpace (as was ſaid) from his ſecond coming to that third, when (namely at his third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) he will ſit upon that great white throne, as Judg, from whoſe face the Earth and Heavens will then ſlee away, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. after the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed. <hi>ver.</hi> 11, 12 to the end: Alſo concerning this third coming ſeems St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo to ſpeak, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. which words are ſpoken to the terrour of ungodly men, termed there, <hi>Scoffers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106268:5"/>at the promiſe of his coming,</hi> whom that laſt coming doth ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, and yet with the exceptive particle, <hi>Nevertheleſs,</hi> brings in the conſolation for the Godly from the promiſe of the new Heavens and the new Earth, which before in the thouſand years they ſhould enjoy with him, <hi>v.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Mr. <hi>Archer</hi> obſerves, firſt his ſecond coming, from <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.30. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his third from <hi>ver.</hi> 31. ſutable to what St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. where he ſpeaks of his firſt coming, <hi>v.</hi> 23. ſaying, <hi>Chriſt the firſt fruits, afterwards</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>they that are Chriſt's at his coming. Then</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſaith he, <hi>cometh the end:</hi> where the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> are uſed at a great diſtance; for Chriſt, the firſt fruits, aroſe before the Saints at his next coming, above 1600 years; and then (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the end cometh, above a thouſand years after his ſaid ſecond coming; and at his third, when the laſt Seſſion of the day of Judgment will be held and finiſhed. Where he further alſo (<hi>v.</hi> 24.) ſets down what muſt be done at that third coming, with what was done before that, all along the thouſand years from the ſecond, while he is putting down all Rule and Authority and Power (<hi>viz.</hi> that oppoſed his own, and ſtood in his way to rule, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) that is, when the Devil ſhall be bound, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.1, 2. wicked men deſtroyed, or made ſlaves, and ſo made his foot-ſtool, at the end of his ſitting at the right-hand of his Father, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. when Antichriſt is deſtroyed (as before) <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. &amp; 19. before his third coming, as might be cleared from many other Texts likewiſe; and alſo the <hi>Turk</hi> come to his end when none ſhall help him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. ver. <hi>ult.</hi> &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. and thereupon aſſerts Chriſt's Reign neceſſarily, v. 25. <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Chriſt muſt reign till he hath put all his enemies under his feet:</hi> and he names the laſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to be deſtroyed by him, namely, <hi>Death,</hi> v. 26. which will be done at his third coming, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. latter end, when <hi>Death and Hell ſhall be caſt into the lake of fire, &amp;c.</hi> ſhews alſo (ver. 24.) when the end ſhall come, and not before, namely, when he ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to God, even the Father, which he received of him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. which he told his Diſciples, he gave to them as his Father had given to him, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. &amp; 1.33. and the glory in that Kingdom which his Father had given to him, he gave to them, <hi>John</hi> 17.22. Alſo of his laſt, or third coming, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks again evidently, ver. 52. of that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. when alſo <hi>the laſt Trump ſhall ſound</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and the dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye;</hi> (and he repeats it again, that it might be obſerved well) <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he again) <hi>the Trumpet ſhall ſound, and the Dead ſhall be raiſed incorruptible, and we ſhall be changed.</hi> Likewiſe in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.3. the Diſciples propound three Queſtions to our Saviour, firſt, of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106268:5"/>deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the ſecond of his coming, namely, his nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> coming, and the third, of the end of the World, which will be at his third (as was ſhewed) he anſwers to them all (though there ſeems to be ſome intermixing) but of his ſecond he ſpeaks <hi>ver.</hi> 30. when all the Tribes of the Earth ſhall mourn, when they ſee him, the Son of man, coming in the Clouds of Heaven with Power and great Glory, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13. But of his third he ſpeaks, <hi>v.</hi> 21. when he ſhall ſend his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with a great ſound of a Trumpet, and they ſhall gather the Elect from the four winds, from one end of Heaven to the other, as 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. So that if we duly weigh and conſider theſe many Texts of holy Scripture, and of others like them, we need not ſo much ſtartle at the mention of Chriſt's third coming, as many upon miſtake, or prejudice and un-grounded conceits, are often apt to do. And as for that Text of <hi>Acts</hi> 3. at the reſtitution of all things, God will ſend Jeſus, whom the Heavens muſt contain till then, <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. it is clearly meant of his ſecond coming, with <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13. when he will come in the Clouds of Heaven; of which three of the Evangeliſts ſpeak in ſeveral places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.30. &amp; 26.44. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.26. &amp; 14.62. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.27. and in <hi>Luke</hi> 21. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. our Saviour ſets forth divers ſigns of that his ſecond coming, and limits thoſe ſigns to the times of the <hi>Jews</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſion; ſaying, <hi>This Generation ſhall not paſs away till all theſe things be fulfilled;</hi> which is to be underſtood of that Nation kept diſtinct from all others till his coming again: Where note, (that his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is never called his laſt coming, as many conceit it to be;) which the hand of God's providence, reſpecting the <hi>Jews,</hi> hath ordered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly ever ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> rejection, though they have been ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered through the World. And agreeable to this the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,</hi> ſignifying a race, ſtock, or off-ſpring of any ſort of men; not an age or preſent time (as ſome unwarrantably would underſtand it) is to be interpreted: and almoſt to this day (accordingly) where the <hi>Jews</hi> have come, they have been for the moſt part known to be <hi>Jews</hi> diſtinct from all other people, and like to be ſo till Chriſt's perſonal appearance to convert them, and deliver them ſuddenly both tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and ſpiritually, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.9. &amp; 12.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe the clearing up the diſtinction of the ſecond and third coming of Chriſt, both of which will be perſonal, are of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in matters reſpecting the laſt times, and by the over-ruling hand of God, Satan and the Antichriſtian faction have all along prevailed to cloud this ſtrongly aſſerted Truth in holy Scriptures, and prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hitherto amongſt men have much prevailed againſt it, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed notion of the general day of Judgment, taken up only upon truſt: we ſhall proceed to conſider the other particular heads following con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106268:6"/>this great ſubject in order, upon which many other myſteries of theſe latter times much depend, according to the warrant we find in ſacred writ, and as the Spirit of God ſhall therein afford aſſiſtance; Namely, in conſidering, <hi>firſt,</hi> the diſtinct times and orders of Chriſt's ſaid ſecond and third perſonal comings, according to the ſeries of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> Viſions and the Book of <hi>Revelation. Secondly,</hi> of the different titles and names of them according to their natures, implying the reaſons of ſuch titles or names. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Of the different things or matters to be done, at both thoſe perſonal comings, in many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then we may take notice of the diſtinct times of the two Seſſions of the great day of Judgment, when he is ſaid to come at both, according to the ſeries or order both of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation;</hi> wherein we have ſummarily ſet down the general heads of Prophecy in their order, as the Spirit of God hath been pleaſed to record them, for the benefit of his Church, for
<note place="margin">See Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel on Chriſt's Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</note> for
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>From the beginning of</hi> Daniel's <hi>Viſions at</hi> Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar <hi>the head of Gold,</hi> Dan. 2. <hi>to Chriſt's third com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are contained above</hi> 3300 <hi>years, as follow; firſt, The time of the Babylonian Captivity, ſeventy years.</hi> 2dly, <hi>From</hi> Cyrus, <hi>in whom the Perſian Monarchy began, to the twentieth year of</hi> Artaxerxes Longimanus, <hi>eighty years.</hi> 3dly, Daniel's <hi>ſeventy weeks, or four hundred ninety years, to the end of the half week after Chriſts death; whoſe death was about</hi> 1666 <hi>years more before Chriſts ſecond perſonal coming (according to all the four computations of Scripture, obſerved) to end about the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen hundredth year of our Lord [ſo that accordingly from his Aſcenſion to his deſcending again, is ſo reckoned</hi> 1666 <hi>years] when the Beaſt will wholly be deſtroyed, (which is to be obſerved.) From thence are to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſts reign with his bleſſed and holy raiſed Saints on Earth a thouſand years: whereunto will ſucceed the little ſeaſon, wherein Satan will be again looſed, to the deſtruction of the laſt Gog &amp; Magog by fire from heaven, which ſince Chriſt ſaith it will be but a little ſeaſon, we have reaſon to believe it will be ſo: whereunto will enſue the laſt Reſurrection and general Judgment: this laſt ſtate of things our Saviour hath clearly &amp; diſtinctly opened,</hi> Rev. 20. <hi>which</hi> Daniel <hi>had but darkly ſet down in ſuch manner as God's Spirit then taught and guided him, for ſuch time as God was pleaſed to have many things which he delivered then to be ſhut up til the time of the end, when Chriſt ſhould unſeal and open them, as both</hi> Daniel <hi>and the</hi> Revelation, <hi>do witneſs.</hi>
               </note> the ſpace (as was ſaid) of above 3300 years of <hi>Daniel's</hi> Prophecies, beginning with the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> who (darkly) hold out the generals of things to be fulfilled in their order to the end of the World, ſaving we finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing there of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpace after <hi>Chriſts</hi> Reign the thouſand years is ended: which both for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and what was to be done in the little ſpace after, our Savior, the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and faithfull Witneſs, hath made known to his Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and which could not by any wiſdom of creatures otherwiſe be found out; and the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt explains ſo much of <hi>Daniel's</hi> Prophecy,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106268:6"/>(though myſtically) as was to be fulfilled to the end, from the time of the opening of the firſt Seal under the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour at his Reſurrection, having received all Power in Heaven and Earth, gave Commiſſion for the preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. Now for the time of Chriſt's ſecond coming, both <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. joyntly agree, (as all ſerious men acquainted with the order of myſtical Prophecies univerſally agree) and is evidently diſcernable to any unprejudiced ſearchers into them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this <hi>Epitome</hi> of that Coming to deſtroy Antichriſt, which both <hi>Daniel</hi> and Chriſt are large in, ſaying, <hi>Chriſt will deſtroy him with the appearance of his Coming:</hi> and ſo in other Scriptures before: <hi>Daniel</hi> hath much in generals that ſhall be in the world at the ſecond perſonal coming of Chriſt, but the third I find not that he hath any touch of, whence the <hi>Jews</hi> did ſo much expect and ſpeak of ſuch a coming, as his ſecond will be, to reſtore the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> which, ſaith Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> the Jewiſh Doctors call the day of the great Judgement, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dies judicii, &amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>magnus dies judicii,</hi> in the 4th Letter to Mr. <hi>Hain:</hi> from <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10.22.26. But our Saviour moſt clearly, and St. <hi>Paul</hi> (and <hi>Peter</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſeems) but eſpecially Chriſt in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> chap. 20. hath ſet forth his third coming, as a point of Doctrine moſt needful to be known and conſidered in the laſt times when his ſecond coming ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth near unto us: As the order of <hi>Daniel's</hi> Prophecy in our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment, and the order of the <hi>Revelation</hi> in the Letter of <hi>May</hi> 20. in the <hi>Fore-runner,</hi> pag. 22. and the ſum of the <hi>Revelation</hi> in the <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will evidently make to appear; ſo that both <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> do orderly hold out his ſecond perſonal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with other Scriptures: And the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt moſt clearly decyphers the third, ſhewing what ſhall be done at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, and all along the thouſand years, and what at the end of them, and how the day of the laſt general Judgment will be brought on and executed to the end of that 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chapter, with the ſtate of things in the <hi>interim</hi> in the two laſt chapters, &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. to the end: which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the ſame time, or at leaſt the entrance upon that period.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, As theſe two perſonall comings are diſtinguiſhed by Chriſt the great Interpreter of both theſe Prophetical Books, ſo their names and decypherings in Scripture are much diſtinguiſhed ſuitable to the nature of both the ſaid comings: The firſt is called, <hi>the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>the appearance of his Coming,</hi> the other his <hi>deſcending from Heaven with a ſhout, &amp;c.</hi> The firſt is his <hi>coming with clouds, &amp;c.</hi> at the other no mention of clouds, but contrarily <hi>Heaven and Earth will then flee away before him:</hi> the former ſtiled the <hi>Revelation of Chriſt when the myſtery of Godlineſs is finiſhed,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. but the laſt will be
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106268:7"/>after a long manifeſtation of his Glory all the thouſand years in the world, with other names more fully to be ſeen in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, pag. 43.44, 45. and the reaſon the former is ſo often called his appearance, ſeemes to be, becauſe Chriſt at his coming in the clouds of Heaven, then will only appear in clouds to the world (no mortal eye being able to behold his Glory in the brightneſs of it) and (probably) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this appearance will be in the clouds but a ſhort time, cheifly to be ſo manifeſt unto the Jewes, to take off the hard vail of unbelief from their hearts; and (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> probably conceives) he will ſpeak to the Jewes (then) at their converſion, as he did to St. <hi>Paul</hi> for a pattern thereof. And after that done, I find not that he wil any more be ſeen of mortal men (at leaſt not ordinarily) in the world; though his Glory will ſhine fully, and inlighten the raiſed Saints in the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as in many texts we have ſhewed, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But his third coming is ſtiled, his <hi>deſcending from Heaven with the voice of an Archangel, and with the Trump of God,</hi> but not ſo at the former, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31. his coming in his Glory with all his holy Angels, and ſitting upon his Throne, where all ſhall be gathered before him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31. and the like in ſeveral texts fore-cited.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As they differ in a long diſtance of time, and the titles given to each according to their natures, ſo they differ in the things that will be done at both thoſe perſonal comings. At the firſt God begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to make Chriſt's foes his foot-ſtool, both by binding of Satan, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and by deſtroying many wicked men from off the earth that would not have him rule over them, &amp; miraculouſly calling the Nation of the Jews, and delivering that Nation fully from their temporal, and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (at leaſt) from their ſpiritual bondage, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and making the wicked to be ſlaves, and likewiſe then brings ſuch as ſleep in Jeſus with him, and all his Saints with him, when the New Jeruſalem comes down from God out of Heaven, which is that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> whoſe maker and builder God is ſaid to be, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. and that City prepared for the fore-fathers, who without us that believe, will not be made perfect <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where the bleſſed and holy raiſed Saints ſhal behold Chriſts glory, which he hath given them their part in, <hi>John</hi> 17.22, 24. and ſhall raign with him there the thouſand years.</p>
            <p>But the third coming of Chriſt, will be <hi>his deſcending from Heaven with a ſhout and the voyce of the Arch-Angel,</hi> as was ſaid, <hi>and with the Trump of God,</hi> above 1000 years after the former, to raiſe firſt thoſe dead in Chriſt, that had died from the time of his appearance at the begining of his thouſand years raign, till his laſt coming; and to change ſuch as were in the natural life, in a moment, inſtead of a death,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106268:7"/>who alltogether, with ſuch as were made alive, and to remain by a powerful reſurrection in the thouſand years, ſhould then alſo be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gather rapt up into the aire to meet Chriſt; and thenceforth ever to be with the Lord; which the Saints raiſed before were not, in the little ſpace when Satan was looſed after the end of the thouſand years; and then ſuddenly (after ſuch a rapture of all the Saints to meet Chriſt in the air) all the wicked will be raiſed to the laſt Judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. at Chriſt ſecond coming he brought all the deceaſed Saints with him; but at his third, all the other, after deceaſed and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Earth, ſhall be raiſed and changed, and with all the former be kapt up altogether to meet him in the air (for none muſt in that (as the Appoſtle ſaith) prevent the other) before only the Juſt that had died, were raiſed up in their order, in the thouſand years, to have their time and meaſure of glory then with Chriſt in the New Jeruſalem, that came down from God, (for every faithful ſufferer for Chriſt in the Kingdom of patience ſhall then reigne with Chriſt in the Kingdom of power on Earth:) but all the other, both good and bad, that lived not again (as they are decyphered) <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. till the thouſand years were ended, ſhal then be raiſed or changed, as was ſaid at Chriſts laſt coming, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before Chriſt came with clouds, to vail his wonderful Glory, that he might be ſeen by mortal eyes, and eſpecially of the Jews, to convert them (therfore called <hi>his appearance,</hi> as we noted) that <hi>that Nation might be born in a day,</hi> as the Scriptures declare, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. and <hi>the iniquity of that Land might be taken away in one day,</hi> as is ſaid, <hi>Zac.</hi> 3.9. But at his laſt coming he will ſhine out in the fulneſs of his glory, and his Saints ſhall be like him (then) in their degree: at his former coming will be but a partial deſtruction upon the wicked world, compared to <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha, &amp;c. Luk.</hi> 17. upon the Armies of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and ſuch as he ſends not his Angels, then to ſave them, as he did <hi>Lot</hi> and his Family, the Lord being merciful unto them: when two will be in one bed, two in the field, two women in the Mill, the one taken, the other left: But at his laſt coming Heaven and Earth will both at once flee away before his face, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and no place be found for them: the Sun Moon and Stars all (then) loſing their light and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when nothing but the light of the glory of Lord, and of his glorious Angels and Saints will ſhine out (then) in the world, to the wonderful rejoycing of the bleſſed, and the terrour and amazement of wicked men and Devils.</p>
            <p>Many ſuch like different conſiderations, I dout not, but God will ſhew to humble and faithful ſearchers into theſe great things of the laſt times, which the Scripture gives Teſtimony unto, which the hazard and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106268:8"/>charge of printing, with other reaſons, barre me at preſent to inlarge upon, or ſo by application to improve them, as otherwiſe was meet, and as the matter requires. Yet I hope by what hath been already laid down, a plain way may be laid open for others, whom God may guide into the like paths, to proceed profitably therein, to ſome greater mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of diſcoverry, and (happily) upon more outwardly helpful advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages then (peradventure) I have found from men; Yet nevertheleſs that a ſpecial divine aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit hath been with me graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly herein, I muſt ever thankfully acknowledge to the praiſe of the riches of his grace towards ſuch a poor, weak, and unworthy inſtrument: who am therefore ſo much the more obliged to render all the glory thereof, unto his Divine Majeſtie. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding I ſhall a little endeavour, according to what I find ſacred Scriptures point out to me, on this or the like account, by way of improvement of this great and weighty ſubject, to give ſome brief hints, at leaſt, to thoſe purpoſes, and leave the inlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof to all truly Chriſtian Spirits for their own uſe and others, only thereunto adjoyning my earneſt and hearty prayers for a bleſſing upon all ſorts in the right uſe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> then, let all faithful Miniſters and Superiors conſider, for their own benefit, this terrour of the Lord, that thereby they may be the more effectually moved, to perſwade men, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. and cheifly ſuch as are under their charge, and all within their reach, upon all advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which God puts into their hands &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let all ſuch arm themſelves with the whole armor of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.11, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. and help to arme others againſt any of Satans moſt violent aſſaults, which God puts into their hand; for Satan, knowing his time is ſhort, hath the more rage againſt all the faithful, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let all hence learn to exerciſe this three-fold watch, upon this account, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.41. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.33, 34, 35, 36, 37. 1ſt. <hi>Watch and be ſober;</hi> in affections of temporal things, in paſſions, in opinion, in practices, avoiding whatever Gods word condemns, as drunkenneſs, or is contrary to true Chriſtian moderation, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.34. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. 2ly. <hi>Watch and pray</hi> (as our Saviour frequently chargeth upon this account) <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.36. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.42. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.38. &amp; 13.33. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7. 3ly. <hi>Watch and keep their garments, Rev.</hi> 16.15. of Juſtification, Sanctification, and an holy Converſation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let all that ſeek their own or others chief and true good, take more care and pains by reaſon of ſuch diſovery of Chriſt's coming approaching, to preſerve and ſecure the ſafety of their own and others ſouls, upon that account; and leſs care then ever for the procuring or
<pb facs="tcp:106268:8"/>ſecuring of temporal things to themſelves, or others: this being Gods undertaking to caſt in unto the other, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. though now the contrary is ſadly obſervable, in this decrepit age of the world, which is now about to leave men, and yet men purſue and cling to it more then ever in former ages, when they were more like to be taken out of it, then that (as now) the world was about to leave them; God in our due uſe of means hath undertaken for our temporals, but it was ever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation our duty to take care for Spirituals; which in the due uſe of all God's means, and in God's way, we can never be too care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for in reſpect of our own or others ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>Fiftly,</hi> Let us approve our ſelves wiſe Virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. by getting Oyl into our Lamps, and to have our Lights burning; that true Grace in our hearts may ſhine forth in our lives; the beſt adornings for the coming of our Lord; that ſo we may be counted worthy to eſcape all thoſe things, and be able to ſtand before him, the Son of man, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. being ſo adorned to meet our ſpiritual Bridegroom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.13. ſo waiting for and expecting the Adoption, even the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of our bodies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. in that day of Redemption when he cometh, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.28. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.33. being then counted worthy of that world, even the world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. and of the reſurrection of the dead, being the children of the reſurrection, <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35. Yea, <hi>let us</hi> (as the Apoſtle exhorteth) <hi>haſten unto the coming of the Lord,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.12. <hi>caſting off every weight that preſſeth down,</hi> Heb. 12.1. and ſo all ſuch as are riſen with Chriſt from the dead, though they ſleep in Jeſus, will God bring with him, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.13. &amp; 4.14.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Sixtly,</hi> Let the due conſideration of this ſecond coming of Chriſt make us long for it, and love it, which will be an Argument of our bleſſedneſs by it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>for there is laid up a Crown of Righteouſneſs for all ſuch as love his appearing;</hi> It is the time of the redemption of all God's <hi>Iſrael</hi> from their Enemies, and from the hands of all that hate them, that <hi>they may ſerve him without fear, in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and holineſs all the dayes of their lives,</hi> Luk. 1.74.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3</note> It is the end and attainment of the faith and prayers of God's People, according to the mercy promiſed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the forefathers, and recorded in the Word, that as our Saviour taught us to pray <hi>that Gods Name ſhould be hallowed, his Kingdom come, his Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven:</hi> ſo it will from his ſaid appearance be accordingly fulfilled, by Angels and Men on Earth (then) as before in Heaven; ſo it will be ſuch a ſtate as will be much admired, and ſo to be longed after &amp; loved: where, above all, his Servants ſhall behold Chriſts glory which his Father hath given him on Earth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Let all faithful Chriſtians hence be chearful and free-hearted in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to Chriſt's Diſciples, ſo making them friends of the <hi>Mammon</hi> of iniquity, that they may receive them into everlaſting habitations, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.9. that which is ſo diſpoſed of, is laid up in the beſt and ſafeſt treaſury in the whole world: yea more, it is put into the beſt hand, and for the beſt improvement that it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to make of earthly treaſure; Chriſt takes it as done to himſelf, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the repayment both more incomparably, than worldly treaſure is worth, and for unſpeakably longer continuance than any worldly treaſure could be kept. 2dly. Be ſitted for acts of ſelf-denial when Chriſt calls to it, for he will be above all our intereſts or relations (as there is the greateſt reaſon, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37.) it is the condition of Chriſt's Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.34. and ſuch as in ſo doing forſake any thing, make Chriſt their debtor who is their beſt paymaſter, and in the beſt ſeaſon: probably in his Kingdom in this time (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the word may ſeem to note) <hi>an hundred fold</hi> in both theſe Texts, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30. &amp; <hi>Luke</hi> 18.30. though otherwiſe, many times in this life, likewiſe: but it is moſt
<pb facs="tcp:106268:9"/>ſure, if they ſuffer with him in <hi>his Kingdom of Patience on Earth,</hi> they man reign with him in <hi>his glorious Kingdom of Power on Earth</hi> in the New Jeruſalem <hi>[Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah Shamma]</hi> the Lord is there, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40. <hi>ult.</hi> and when the Tabernacle of God is with men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3. and he will dwell with them, and wipe away all tears from their eyes. And 3dly. to be couragious and reſolute in ſuffering for him when called to this: And what are any or all the ſufferings of men, to the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of God becoming man? that he might ſuffer to ſatisfie Divine Juſtice, to procure infinite Mercy for ſuch as ſhould otherwiſe have endured infinite and eternal Miſery: this our Saviour requires in the forenamed places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.23. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.34.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> Let the terrible things of both thoſe comings engage Godly men to labour to be counted worthy to eſcape ſuch things, and to be able to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Son of man; by improving all ſuch Chriſts and his Spirits counſels, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. as ye have heard in ſundry particulars. And let the conſideration of them fray wicked men from their ſins, even the greateſt as well as the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: and to learn to kiſs the Son, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2 <hi>ult.</hi> leſt he be angry, and they periſh in the way: And if they will not believe theſe things, let them hence know aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly they will feel the miſery of them, as the <hi>Jews</hi> of old did after Chriſt's firſt coming, upon their neglecting or deſpiſing his warnings.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
               <hi>Again.</hi> As for ungo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly men of any of the former ſorts, that refuſe to make any ſuch good uſe of theſe terrors of the Lord, let them hence alſo take notice and know, that when they ſhall think themſelves moſt ſecure in their ſins, a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den deſtruction will then come upon them, as pains on a woman in travel, and they ſhall not eſcape. It is true (I know) and I find by daily experience, that theſe terrors of the Lord, and Doctrines of mortification are unpleaſing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceptable to moſt ſorts of men, but they muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e preſſed upon them; as whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and neceſſary Phyſick is by parents upon their children to ſave their lives, ſo on theſe to ſave ſuch mens ſouls (if God may give them repentance:) but if not, they will be the more inexcuſable, in that they have not periſhed without warning, and ſuch ſeaſonable warnings may help to free Gods Miniſters from the heavy guilt of the blood of ſouls. Now therefore let all carnal, worldly, ignorant, prophane, wicked, and u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> believing perſons: And all ſinfully engaged enemies to the Truth, Cauſe, Glory, Worſhip and Servants of God, or againſt any or all ſorts of perſons engaged to ſtand up for Gods and Chriſts ſake, that ſo they might promote irreligion and falſe religion with prophaneneſs; or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſuppreſs true Religion and the power of Religion by oppoſition and hatred of true Piety and Holineſs: Oh, let ſuch ſeriouſly and throughly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, in the moſt retired cloſets of heir hearts and conſciences, what a dreadful appearance (without repentance and reformation) will the coming of the Lord be unto all ſuch! O let them conſider what fools they will then be (with millions of witneſſes) that for trifles, ſading Vanities, for nothing, for worſe than nothing, for the matter and cauſe of horrour and anguiſh, with everlaſting wo and miſery, in that they have deſpiſed &amp; rejected their own mercy, that happineſs that Chriſt hath purchaſed, by an infinite price, and was provided for his ſervants, by the moſt wife, holy, glorious, and infinitely gracious God, for all truly penitent and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving ſouls, and tendered and beſtowed on them by the ſanctifying Spirit of Wiſdom, Grace and Truth; but ſuch in the mean time while it is offered will have none of it, but utterly reject it, and all God's and Chriſt's terms whereupon it is offered to them: How then can they think to ſtand, when Gods wrath and fury ſhall break out againſt them, and they be irrecoverably carried away with the ſtreams of his eternal indignation: Let this (I ſay) be duly conſidered by all ſorts of ſuch perſons while time and opportunity laſteth; and who knows how ſuddenly any mans opportunity may be loſt irrecoverably? &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106268:9"/>
            <head>Certain Obſervations, uſeful for the underſtanding of divers Myſtical Prophecres of holy Scriptures,
<note place="margin">See the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 53, 54, 55.</note> reſpecting the latter dayes, for the encreaſe of Joy and Conſolation to faithfull Chriſtians.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>FIrſt,</hi> Where things that concern the Myſteries of the laſt times are expreſſed more fully in the Old Teſtament, they are uſually touched more briefly in the New: as for example, What is ſaid of that <hi>Mother-Text, Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> calls it) of the firſt Seſſion of the Great Day of Judgement, or <hi>the Judgement of the Great Day,</hi> (as St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks) ſetting forth God's manner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Antichriſt, as is ſaid, remarkably; becauſe of the great words the Horn ſpake, &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. That is, for the Popes abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Blaſphemies, Tyranny, Pride and inſolent Impieties, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which in the New-Teſtament is but briefly, many times, ſet down, as 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>whom he ſhall deſtroy with the appearance of his coming;</hi> the like, chap. 1.7, 8, 9. of which and the like Scriptures in the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſaid text, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. was the ground and warrant; ſave only in the order of the accompliſhment St. <hi>John</hi> had a particular Viſion to the like purpoſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, 11. to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The firſt ſaid Seſſion of the Great Day of Judgement will be for the deſtruction of the firſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to wit, of the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> who were ſo under thoſe terms repreſented to the Jews, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.39. before the ſetting up of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem, Ezek.</hi> 40. to the end of that Book; and the ſecond Seſſion will be upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the ſecond <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> above a thouſand years after, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. at the end of the world. Where again obſerve, that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> are taken for the great, obſtinate, reſolved Enemies of God's People, whom he will powerfully deſtroy. Now at both the ſaid Seſſions of the great Day, and at the ruine of both ſorts of thoſe wicked men, it is ſaid, that <hi>the Judgment was ſet, and the Books were opened,</hi> which ſeem proper to the Judgment of the great Day, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 14. And again, obſerve,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of Roman Mon. the</hi> 6th <hi>head.</hi>
               </note> that at both the ſaid Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, quick and dead are ſaid to be judged: Firſt, the wicked quick, namely, Antichriſt and his followers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then to be ſent to the Lake of Fire and Brimſtone, from the <hi>Armageddon</hi>-battel, deſcribed <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. from ver. 11. to the 20th. Concerning the ſame it is again ſaid
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106268:10"/>of the ſame time when the third Wo came, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. <hi>Thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them that deſtroyed the Earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 99.</note> when the Nations were angry, and God's Wrath was then come, as the twenty four Elders that praiſe God for the ruine of Antichriſt at that time, and likewiſe for judging the dead (then) by giving reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and to his Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> conceives he will be doing all the thouſand years, Raiſing the Saints in their own order (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks) which is called by Chriſt <hi>the firſt Reſurrection, Rev.</hi> 20.5. and of which St. <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh remarkably, when he had ſpoken of Chriſt's Reſurrection as the firſt fruits thereof, which was to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1600 years before, then ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>afterwards they that are Chriſts at his coming,</hi> namely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, at his coming or preſence, at Antichriſt's deſtruction; and then (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) he ſpeaks of the coming, of the end, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23, 24. which Chriſt ſhews ſhould be above a thouſand years after the former, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. namely, (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> further adds) when Chriſt had put down all Rule, all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Power, and when he had deſtroyed the laſt enemy, Death, ver. 26. Which Chriſt again ſhews ſhall be done at his laſt Seſſion of Judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. before he gives up again the Kingdom to his Father, and until that time St. <hi>Paul</hi> poſitively aſſerts the Reign of Chriſt in the world, namely, from his ſecond Coming or Appearance to the end of the ſecond Seſſion of the Judgment of the Great Day,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cov.</hi> next after the <hi>Parall.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he muſt reign till he hath put all his Enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his feet;</hi> which Reign Chriſt teacheth muſt be a thouſand years, with his eminent Saints firſt raiſed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and at the end like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe quick and dead will be again both judged: firſt, the wicked quick (then) at the deſtruction of the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and then the dead both good and bad when the reſt of the dead ſhall be raiſed, as they are called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. &amp; 12.13.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The deſcription of the New-Jeruſalem, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40. to the end of the Book, whoſe name is there ſaid to be <hi>Jehovah Shamma,</hi> or <hi>the Lord is there;</hi> becauſe there his Saints ſhall behold his glory given to him in his Kingdom on Earth, as Mediator, for a reward in time of that his great work in time, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14, 15. which by his laſt Will and Teſtament in the preſence of his Father and his Diſciples he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared at the end of that Prayer,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Obſ.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> 17.24. after he had ended his Farewel-Sermon, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. and then the Lamb will be the viſible light of that heavenly City, come down from God out of Heaven, whoſe maker and builder is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. to remain in the world above a thouſand years. But (I ſay) that deſcription of the ſaid City in the Old Teſtament ſeems there to be ſet forth ſutably to the ſtate of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106268:10"/>Jews under the Old Teſtament, when <hi>Ezekiel</hi> was their Prophet. But the deſcription of the New Jeruſalem under the New Teſtament (which upon many conſiderations from the context, and the ſeries of the times, which both deſcriptions relate unto, appear plainly to be one and the ſame thing) I ſay, that Deſcription of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. is ſet forth more ſutably to the ſtate of the Chriſtian Church in a more glorious manner, unto which a more eminent degree of Chriſt's Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was manifeſt, before that triumphant State of it came, which ſhould ſo deſcend from God out of Heaven, to be for ſuch time in the world; which conſiſting of the raiſed Saints, is not only called <hi>The Beloved City,</hi> which thoſe bleſſed and holy ones at their reſurrection (as they are called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6.) ſhall then inhabit, and have manſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, (and the holy Jeruſalem, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.10.) for the time of their reign with Chriſt there; But they being in it then <hi>made one,</hi> and <hi>perfect in one,</hi> as Chriſt prayed, <hi>John</hi> 17.11. <hi>as Chriſt and the Father are one, &amp;c.</hi> (conſider well the Prayer of Chriſt, being all along prophetical of the enſuing times) that Jeruſalem will be then the Bride, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. and the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and was of old fore-ſpoken of, as his Spouſe, in the <hi>Song of Solomon,</hi> his type therein: So the Wiſdom of God ſeems to fit the deſcriptions thereof ſuitably to their ſeveral ſtates to whom it was ſo repreſented.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The moſt of thoſe Prophecies which concern the Jews are more fully ſet forth in the Old Teſtament. Hence the <hi>Turk's</hi> ruine, who is the ſixth Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. is more fully deſcribed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, 39 chapters, under the name of <hi>Gog,</hi> and the <hi>Pope's</hi> there both briefly under the name of <hi>Magog,</hi> in chap. 39. referring us Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans intime to come, to look into the New Teſtament, for what God would after, for our uſe then make known of Antichriſt more largely.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> The fifth and ſixth Trumpets, which are the firſt and ſecond Wo-Trumpets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.
<note place="margin">See <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgm. Dan.</hi> 11.40.</note> which were to ruine the Eaſtern Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, are the <hi>Sarazens</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> ſet forth by the titles of the <hi>King of the South,</hi> and <hi>the King of the North, Dan.</hi> 11.40, &amp;c. being likewiſe the oppreſſors of the poor Jews.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> The <hi>Armageddon-battel</hi> being for the deſtruction of the firſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> is ſet forth in both Teſtaments, as referring to the Enemies of both Chriſtian Jews, and Gentiles, firſt ſet down in the Old Teſtament, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, 39 chapters, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.7, 11, 12. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. &amp; <hi>Zech.</hi> 14. as in reference to the Jews. Secondly, in the New-Teſtament, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14 &amp; 15 chapters, and 16th under or after the ſixth Viol, and <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in reference to the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> The greatly-beloved Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> chiefly ſets down
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106268:11"/>what might be ground of comfort to the faithful Jews:
<note place="margin">See <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 63.</note> But the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Diſciple and Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> mainly ſpeaks of what might be uſeful for the Faithful in the times of the Gentiles, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. whilſt the body of the Jewiſh Nation remained caſt out.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> The 12th chapter of <hi>Daniel's</hi> Prophecy is uſeful to open the way for underſtanding the Myſteries of that Book, as the 17th chapter of the <hi>Revelations</hi> is for the underſtanding much in that Book.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Abridgm.</hi> on <hi>Dan.</hi> chap. 12.</note> For from <hi>Daniels</hi> 12th may be underſtood the time and order of Chriſts appearing, with the terribleneſs thereof, ver. 1. and of the Jews deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance therewith, v. 1. and how long before both will come, v. 11, 12. and what ſtate that Church and the Saints in it ſhould be in then, v. 1, 13. in what ſtate the Church of the Jews was in before Chriſt's appearing, very troubleſom, v. 2, 3. how long theſe Myſteries ſhould continue ſhut up, v. 4, 9. and what was meant by the time of the end when they ſhould be opened, compare ver. 9. with verſe 40 of chap. 11. and then what ſtate was to be of the Church of the Gentiles, ver. 4. latter part of the verſe, and v. 5, 6, 7. which <hi>Daniel</hi> (then) under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood not, v. 8. becauſe then ſealed up, v. 9. and likewiſe concerned things long after to come in the Gentile-Church, and yet he had it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to him before by one that ſtood by, chap. 7.16, 21 to v. 27. So alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. is a chapter remarkably ſet down by the Spirit of God, very uſeful for the opening of divers Myſteries contained in the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Irenicon,</hi> p. 26, 27, 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> concerning Antichriſt's riſe, reign and ruine, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things thereunto partaining, mentioned chapters 11, 13, 14, 15, 16, &amp;c. as may be obſerved in the Letter of <hi>May</hi> 20. in the <hi>Fore-runner,</hi> and in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> Then obſerve, <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions were ſealed to the time of the end, chap. 12.9. which was to the times of the <hi>Sarazens</hi> &amp; <hi>Turks,</hi> or (which is contemporary) in Antichriſt's time, times, and the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a time, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7. &amp; chap. 7.24, 25. compated with <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. &amp; chap. 11. &amp; chap. 13. at which time they were to be unſealed in reſpect of both thoſe enemies both of Jews and Gentiles, as <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> ſet them forth in their due order, as was ſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> What <hi>Daniel</hi> briefly ſhewed the Jews ſhould be done for them at Chriſt's Appearing,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Abridgm.</hi> on <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.</note> namely, (that then his People ſhould be delivered) <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in that reſpect more fully explained, from the Viſions of God, chap. 37. firſt, by the riſing of the dry bones; and after by the uniting of two ſticks into one under one King, to them both for ever: and chap. 38, 39. by removing <hi>Gog</hi> the hinderer of their riſing. And laſtly, chap. 40, 41, 42, to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106268:11"/>end of the Book, by ſhewing to him the New Jeruſalem then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue after <hi>Gog</hi>'s ruine: and both <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> being God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſent to the Jews in the time of their Captivity, and both fore-telling their great reſtoration, and the time thereof (though myſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) as two witneſſes of God's Truth to comfort the Faithful Jews in the low ebb of their dejected condition till then.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
               <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> The firſt three worldly Monarchies being paſt, which had oppreſſed the Jews before Chriſt came in the fleſh, the Book of <hi>Revelation</hi> ſpeaks nothing of them;
<note place="margin">See <hi>Abridgm. on Dan.</hi>
               </note> nor of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy till Chriſt's Reſurrection, at the opening of the firſt Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. when Chriſt having all power in Heaven and in Earth given to him, he gave Commiſſion to his Diſciples for the preaching of the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 26, 27, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and pag. 61, 62, 63.</note> But afterwards the orders of the times and things in <hi>Daniel,</hi> as reſpecting the proceedings of things in the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, to the time of its ruine, and Chriſt's Kingdom following upon it, both the Prophecy of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Book of <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> exactly agree, as being revealed by the ſame eternal Spirit of Truth, namely, from the finiſhing of Chriſt's work of Redemption to his coming again: But after that for the ſtate of things, in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14, 15. to the end of that chapter, that it ſhall be for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, Chriſt only in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20, 21, &amp; 22. further informs us, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it is darkly imployed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.13. where it is promiſed to <hi>Daniel</hi> that he ſhall ſtand up in his lot at the end of the dayes, that is, at the reſurrection of the Juſt, or firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> Hence it may appear that though Chriſt, as man, upon Earth, knew not the time of the laſt day, yet having ſince aſcended, and ſitting on his Fathers right hand in Heaven, revealed now for our uſe (in a latitude) both concerning the laſt day, and alſo many other great myſteries contained in that Divine Book of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> and by means of that (together with the aſſiſtance of God's holy Spirit) what was ſhut up before in <hi>Daniel</hi> likewiſe, till the time of the end, but ever ſince to be ſought after to be known for the benefit of his Church, as they are recorded by his Apoſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> with promiſe of bleſſing to the due performance thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
               <hi>13ly.</hi> Such Scriptures as have ſpecial ſtamps upon them of the laſt times, as <hi>Jacob's</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> his Prophecies of the twelve Tribes, <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 59, 60, 61.</note> 49. &amp; <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. and that Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> penned for poſterity, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. and <hi>Balaams</hi> Prophecy, <hi>Num.</hi> 24. &amp;c. uſually contain ſomething in them reſpecting the ſame times.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
               <hi>14ly.</hi> That uſual phraſe in Scripture in the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the poſtremity of dayes:</hi> in the Septuagint <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the laſt of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106268:12"/>dayes:</hi> by ours read, <hi>in the latter dayes,</hi> hath reference uſually to theſe Times wherein theſe great Myſteries were to be opened by degrees, and the things contained in them accordingly fulfilled in their orders, as is obſervable in theſe Scriptures following, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.1. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.25. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.20. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38.16. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. But eſpecially take notice of theſe two following places, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.28. &amp; 10.14. to which may be added <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.17. <hi>the time of the end,</hi> and ver. 19. <hi>the laſt end of the indignation;</hi> and the like, chap. 11.36. <hi>till the indignation be accompliſhed:</hi> where the former or ſuch other like expreſſions of the latter dayes are uſed, which all uſually refer to the Myſteries of theſe latter times. But <hi>Daniel</hi> in the firſt text tells <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> expreſly, [<hi>that God had made known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him what ſhould be in the poſtremity of dayes,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>viz.</hi> in the fourth and fifth Monarchies as he proceeds to explain to him: And chap. 10 14. after <hi>Daniel</hi> had ſeen a glorious Viſion of Chriſt, an Angel was ſent to comfort him, and told him expreſly <hi>that he was ſent to make him underſtand what ſhould befall his People in the latter,</hi> or <hi>poſtremity of days:</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <hi>Abridgm.</hi> on <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36, 40</note> and ſo the other like phraſes at the time of the end, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. that is, <hi>in the laſt times:</hi> So chap. 12.4, 9, 13. <hi>in the end of the dayes;</hi> at the reſurrection of the Juſt, that is, when <hi>Daniel</hi> was to be raiſed again to ſtand in his lot: and the other phraſe, <hi>the laſt end of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation,</hi> Dan. 8.19. and chap. 11.36. is to be underſtood of the Jews full &amp; great Reſtoration at Chriſt's Appearance, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. which are the particular drifts of thoſe ſeveral phraſes by the orders of his Viſions and the intents of them (as may appear by their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments in part) and by what is further ſtill to be done, as we have ſet down in their due place in our Abridgment of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions, on divers of thoſe places and phraſes. Therefore, beſides many other conſiderations from the Prophecies of <hi>Daniel,</hi> which might be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly added, take notice of this one; How unwarrantably ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men, contrary to the ſcope of the Spirit of God, and the natural ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of theſe many phraſes and expreſſions ſet down by the holy Ghoſt along that Book, beſides the experimental fulfilling of divers things therein accordingly, as chap. 11.40. &amp; 12.4, 9. &amp; 2.28. in part fulfilled: yet notwithſtanding all theſe, they have (I ſay) very miſtakenly gone about to limit and confine all <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy to the <hi>Greek</hi> Empire, which our Saviour hath manifeſted in the Book of <hi>Revelation,</hi> will not be fulfilled wholly in about two thouſand years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or (happily) near upon it. See our Abridgment on <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the fum of the <hi>Revelation</hi> in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106268:12"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
               <hi>15ly.</hi> God's Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be the Lord his God, and thereupon to give to him and his ſeed the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> renewed afterwards to <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26.3. and alſo to <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 35.12.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Fore runner,</hi> p. 38, 39.</note> and confirmed by <hi>Moſes</hi> for all three together, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.3, 4. yea, and as he ſpeaks, <hi>ſworn by God to them,</hi> Deut. 30.20. Yea and again, with a very remarkable and ſtrong expreſſion, reaching to and comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of Chriſt in the thouſand years, as appears <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.21. <hi>he ſware it</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>as the dayes of Heaven upon Earth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Upon the account of all which God ſeems to tell <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 3. that that ſhould be his Memorial through all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that he was <hi>the God of Abraham, Iſaac, and Jacob;</hi> which Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial he there three times repeated, v. 6, 15, 16. to aſſure all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the firſt Reſurrection of the Juſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5, 6. having not only perſonally promiſed it to them all, but <hi>ſworn it</hi> in ſuch manners as <hi>Moſes</hi> recordeth. And yet again, his own Spirit and Word in his Servants mouths again declares, that in their natural lives they lived on Earth, this Promiſe made perſonally to them was not fulfilled (as St. <hi>Stephen</hi> expreſly ſpeaks, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.5.) they had not ſo much as to ſet a foot upon by that Covenant, (though they purchaſed Burying-places that their dead bones might keep poſſeſſion thereof by that means till the Reſurrection of the Juſt, or firſt ſaid Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5, 6.) when Chriſt that one promiſed Seed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. in ſpecial and chiefly to be underſtood as <hi>their Seed, not Seeds,</hi> as the Apoſtle remarkably diſtinguiſheth, and expoundeth too in that Text: I ſay, Chriſt that promiſed Seed ſhould put them into poſſeſſion then of that Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> wherein they had been only <hi>ſtrangers and pilgrims</hi> before, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9. and <hi>dwelling in Tabernacles,</hi> as was the condition alſo of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſhews, though they were <hi>Heirs of the ſame Promiſe,</hi> ver. 9. and yet he had ſaid of <hi>Abraham</hi> particularly, ver. 8. <hi>That Abraham when he was called to go out into a place which he was afterward to receive for an Inheritance, obeyed, not knowing whither he went:</hi> So that not having yet received it, he muſt (according to Scripture) receive it at the ſaid firſt Reſurrection;
<note place="margin">See <hi>Fore-runner,</hi> p. 38, 39.</note> for God's Promiſes and Oaths will not fail (though many mens faith may much fail in theſe things, as is by our Saviour foretold, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8.) when he <hi>(Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham)</hi> ſhal appear to be the Heir not only of <hi>Canaan</hi> (but of the World) through faith, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> further teacheth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. and this Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſhews to be the drift of our Saviour's Argument, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.27. &amp; <hi>Mark</hi> 12. that therefore God is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> according to the tenour of that Covenant, in that they muſt live again upon Earth to inherit (then) that promiſed Land
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106268:13"/>of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to wit, at that time of the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.19, 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in the New Creation of all things;</hi> as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſhews, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Behold, I make all things new;</hi> and in this ſenſe <hi>Beza</hi> underſtands that place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, according to five or ſix copies, diſtinguiſhed by a comma, to be underſtood in that ſenſe, <hi>of new creation of things,</hi> not ſpiritual regeneration, as men uſe to take it: when all ſuch faithful Spirits ſhall be counted (as our Saviour ſpeaks) worthy to obtain that World, and the Reſurrection of the Dead, that which is called <hi>the World to come,</hi> Heb. 2.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And when <hi>Abraham's, Iſaac</hi>'s, and <hi>Jacob</hi>'s poſterity ſhall enjoy that Land with them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. to ver. 11. &amp; <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. as <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom ſhall then be ſtabliſhed before himſelf for ever to the end, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.16. And ſo likewiſe the Promiſe and Covenant made to <hi>David,</hi> of the Kingdom for himſelf and his Seed for ever, will (then) in Chriſt the Seed of <hi>David</hi> on Earth be fulfilled, when alſo the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s loſt dominion, as was fore-propheſied, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained and applyed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. will be regained to the raiſed Saints from the dead at the firſt ſaid Reſurrection, by Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> Conſider ſeriouſly theſe Scripture-evidences, and the things held out by them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
               <hi>16ly.</hi> Such Prophecies as ſpeak of good things to come to <hi>Iſrael, Ephraim,</hi> or <hi>Joſeph,</hi> together with <hi>Judah</hi> joyned with them, uſually contain ſomething belonging to the great Reſtauration at Chriſt's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing and his Kingdom, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. when he firſt begins to judge quick and dead at the firſt ſeſſion of the day of Judgement: when God's ancient People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall be joyned together into one ſtick, under one King, to them both for ever, even Chriſt being his Promiſed Seed, which will be accompliſhed in thoſe laſt dayes (as was ſaid) from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 
               <hi>17ly.</hi> When <hi>David</hi> by his prophetical Spirit foretelleth of things incompetible to his own Kingdom, or to his natural ſeed, ſuch things muſt neceſſarily be referred to Chriſt's glorious Kingdom on Earth,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 77, 78, 79, 80.</note> in the thouſand years.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> 
               <hi>18ly.</hi> Again, it is obſervable in Myſtical Prophecies, that the Spirit of God ſeems many times to lay down great things in generals, and after by degrees to give expoſitions of them,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Abridgm. on Dan.</hi>
               </note> as in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's</hi> dream, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. and <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions of the ſame matters, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. both which are by <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Angel in the ſame chapters in ſome brief way firſt expounded: and both again more particularly afterwards in the following Viſions in their order, chap. 8. and ſomewhat in chap. 9. but afterwards more fully in many things, in their order, in his laſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106268:13"/>large Viſion, chap. 10, 11, 12. and ſo in the <hi>Revelation</hi> in chap. 4, 5, &amp; 7. ſome general heads are touched at, which are more particularly explained in a great part of the Book following: So in the latter part of chap. 14. the decay of the Papacy is ſpoken of, which afterwards is again explained, chapters 15 &amp; 16, more briefly, and ſome of the Vials again more largely, chapters 18, 19, &amp; 20.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> 
               <hi>19ly.</hi> In the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> when things are not ſaid to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed one the other, as 1ſt, 2d, 3d, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the Seals, Trumpets &amp; Vials, but one meaſure of time is aſſigned and ſuited to them all, or one table of Chronology is fitted to them all, ſuch diſtirct Viſions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries, as all that concerned the true and falſe Church in Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt's time have the ſame meaſure (though diverſly computed) by months, dayes, and a time times and an half; all agreeing in 1260 years, the date of the Beaſt, the mourning-time of the Witneſſes, the Woman's Wilderneſs-condition: by which alſo the Whore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> the ten crowned Horns, with the two-horned Beaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to their ſeaſons: So all thoſe Viſions under or after the 7th Trumpet,
<note place="margin">See the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 30.</note> have one Chronological Table to compute their time [as chap 11. to v. 15. contained the forty two months for the night-workers in darkneſs: and a thouſand two hundred and ſixty dayes of ſuch as are of the Light, and walk therein:] So all the Viſions (I ſay) in the three laſt chapters, have one Chronological Table to compute the time of them all, to wit, [a thouſand years] wherein Chriſt will reign with his Saints, the Devil ſhall be bound and ſhut up, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the New Jeruſalem come down from God, and God's Tabernacle be with men; and the New Heavens and New Earth, and the Paradiſe of God, and the Tree of Life, and the pure River, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all for the ſaid time of the thouſand years, and ſo are contemporaries, and all ſtrongly there aſſerted and confirmed. See <hi>Irenicon</hi> in ſeveral places.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> 20. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> After Chriſt Jeſus our Saviour had finiſhed his Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Sermon, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. he then in the preſence of his Diſciples made that moſt excellent declarative Prayer, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. wherein a large Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of many things to come is very divinely (though myſtically) couched: wherein we may obſerve many things in order, according to the Will of his heavenly Father, ſet forth by Chriſt, which ſhould afterward according both to his prayer, prediction or diſpoſal, be done, and hath herein cauſed to be recorded, which ſhall have their due ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment in their times, begining from his making that excellent prophetical Prayer; who alwayes prayed according to his heavenly Father's Will, and (as he ſaid) was alwayes heard of him: and ſo it is to be known by us, that all here he prayed for, in reſpect of himſelf,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106268:14"/>his Diſciples, and the faithful Paſtors and Chriſtians ſucceeding, even all ſuch as his Father had given him till his coming again, and all that believed through their word, namely the Apoſtles Doctrine, through the time of the wicked world, which he prayed not for till the time of the good world came, that ſhould both believe and know him whom the Father had ſent; when that Glory ſhould be given to his own, that the Father had given him: concerning which he then made his Will, v. 24. that they ſhould behold his Glory in his Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. at the Reſurrection, in that World to come of which he ſpeaks, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36. which, as was ſaid <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. is ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the world</hi> (habitable) <hi>to come,</hi> of which the Apoſtle there ſaid he ſpake, namely chap. 1.6. where he had ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>when he ſhall bring his Son again into the World,</hi> that is, the <hi>ſecond time,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>and let all the Angels of God worſhip him:</hi> for <hi>he ſhall</hi> then (as both <hi>Daniel,</hi> and from <hi>Daniel</hi> three of the Evangeliſts witneſs Chriſt's words of his coming) <hi>come in the clouds of Heaven,</hi> as was foretold of him, <hi>and all his holy ones with him, both Saints and Angels.</hi> And in reference to this order of this prophetical declarative Prayer of our bleſſed Saviour, obſerve the enſuing ſteps of his proceeding therein to the ſaid purpoſes, which we have already hinted, to be now further obſerved and duly conſidered accordingly. Ver. 1. he ſaith, <hi>Father, glorifie thy Son, that thy Son may alſo glorifie thee:</hi> which was evidently ſoon after anſwered in his Reſurrection from the dead; of which God ſaid, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee,</hi> Pſal. 2.7. applyed largely by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to Chriſt's Reſurrection, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.33, 34, 35, 36, 37. with other Scriptures; of which, ſaith he again <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. <hi>he was declared to be the Son of God with power by the reſurrection from the dead:</hi> And being ſo glorified by his Father, he alſo glorified him by ſetting up the preaching of the Goſpel, and give Salvation thereby, v. 2, 3, 4. when all power being given to him in Heaven and in Earth, as he ſaid <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. he then mainly improves the ſame in commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionating and fitting, and ſending his Diſciples to be his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel (as in the Prayer is to be obſerved afterwards) and <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go, preach the Goſpel to all Nations;</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> 15. <hi>Go, preach the Goſpel to every creature;</hi> and alſo glorified his Father many wayes in the forty days after his Reſurrection; but eſpecially he is ſaid then to ſpeak to his Diſciples of the things that concerned the Kingdom of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.3, 4, 5. whereupon ſeemed that queſtion of the ſame Kingdom then to be moved by them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next ſtep was his Prayer for his Aſcenſion into Heaven, v. 5. to be glorified with that Glory which he had before in the Boſom of his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106268:14"/>Father before the world was, when he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward ſhould as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-man</hi> in one perſon, ſit at the right-hand of the Father in his Caeleſtial Glory, which he had with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the world was: and then v. 6, 7, 8. having declared divers things reſpecting his Diſciples, what he had done towards them, and what effect was found in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he proceeds in v. 9, 11. to make his Prayer for his Diſciples, after to be his Apoſtles, being in the world when he was aſcended, that his Father would keep them from that <hi>evil world,</hi> as he had done for them to that time, v. 12. having ſhewed their joynt intereſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. and ſhews the end why he ſpake theſe things ſuitable to their preſent ſtate, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. and ſhewing what Perſecution they were to look for, but how they ſhould be preſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he proceeds to limit his Prayer for his Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>not that they ſhould be taken out of the world, but that they ſhould be kept from the evil:</hi> And ſince they were not of that world, v. 16. he prayes further in v. 17. to have them ſanctified by the Word of God's Truth: and giving them their Miſſion, <hi>v.</hi> 18. he ſhews, the end of his ſanctifying himſelf was for their ſanctification by that means, <hi>v.</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>So having done with what concerned his Diſciples to be ſent as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles into the world, and in them for all faithful Meſſengers of the Goſpel that were to ſucceed: he then proceeds, v. 20. to pray for all truly faithful and believing ſouls <hi>[through their Word]</hi> (as he ſpeaks) even from that time of their Miſſion to his Coming again (as may many wayes appear by what follows from ver. 20. to 25.) wherein all ſuch faithful perſons ſhould be equally concerned; ſhewing that the end and drift of all their believing [through their Word] or of any of his Meſſengers, was, <hi>that they might all be one, as the Father was in him, and he in the Father; that they might be one, as the Father and the Son were one,</hi> v. 21, 22. that is, that they ſhould be, as the Bride, the Lamb's Wife, is one with her Head in the New Jeruſalem, come down from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and ſo made perfect in one, v. 23. at Chriſt's ſecond coming; or his coming again into the world, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. when that good world to come ſhall believe that the Father hath ſent him, yea, and know it too in an eſpecial manner, as he adds and repeats in part the ſame thing, v. 21, 23. having ſhewed in v. 22. that he had given them the ſame Glory that the Father had given him in his Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14, 15. and for that end that they might be one (as was ſaid before) as he and the Father are one, who loved them as he had loved him. And v. 24. he further declares his own laſt Will and Teſtament in that particular, reſpecting the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of that happineſs with himſelf in the ſaid Kingdom which his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106268:15"/>Father had given him, as Mediator, as a reward in time for that work, finiſhed in the time of that his Office, which the Faithful ſhould enjoy with him in the time of that ſaid good World to come, when they ſhould be where he ſhould be, and behold to their happineſs the Glory then given him by his Father, from his love to him, as his obedient Son and faithful Servant, before the foundation of the world: and in the two laſt verſes concludes with ſome ſpecial conſolations reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſciples, as follows, ver. 25, 26. to the end of the chapter.</p>
            <p>Thus divinely hath our bleſſed Saviour, according to his infinite Wiſdom, couched the order of theſe glorious Myſteries, in his making and leaving this moſt excellent Prophetical and declarative Prayer of his before his departure out of the World, recorded by his beloved A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>John,</hi> for the information and conſolation of his poor and little little Flock, to whom, with himſelf, it was his Father's pleaſure to give that Kingdom with himſelf on Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. And the advancement of that ſtate is the great drift of our Lord's Prayer, recorded alſo by two Evangeliſts, namely that God's Name may be hallowed,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 30.</note> and his Kingdom come, and conſequently his Will be doen in Earth (then) as in Heaven (before;) for which purpoſe, as God's People ſhould alwayes endeavour faithfully, ſo they have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant ground to believe from the Word it will be ſo done in the time when the Devil will be ſhut up in the bottomleſs-pit from ſeducing the Nations for a thouſand years ſpace, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. The bleſſed and holy Saints ſhall come with Chriſt to take their bodies in their own order: The glorious Angels ſhall come and worſhip him, and do their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to him in the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. And all the creatures in Heaven and Earth, and under the Earth, ſhall bow the knee, and be ſubject unto him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. and all things be made new by him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. all which ſince his Word declareth moſt ſurely, ſhall be performed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> 21. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That the perfect Dominion over the Creatures (which was part of the Image of God upon Man in his innocency) will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored again unto him, the holy Scriptures make evident; which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>The whole Creation groans for to be delivered from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> Rom. 8. and this <hi>David</hi> prophetically foreſhews will be done in Chriſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8. where he ſaith, <hi>God had viſited him, the Son of man, and made him</hi> for a little time [as both the word in the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and alſo the Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agint [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] ſignifie) <hi>lower than the Angels, and crowned him with Glory and Worſhip,</hi> making him to have dominion over the works of his hands, and putting all things under his feet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle applyes to Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. and alſo ſaith, <hi>he hath made him,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106268:15"/>(<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>a little while</hi> (as our Tranſlation hath it in the margent like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) <hi>inferiour to the Angels;</hi> and then ſpeaketh of the ſame ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the creatures under him, then afterwards to come; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ver. 8. he ſaith, <hi>we do not yet ſee all things put under him:</hi> only <hi>we ſee Chriſt</hi> in his own perſon, that for a little while <hi>was made lower than the Angels, for the ſuffering of death, crowned with glory and honour.</hi> But he again further teacheth, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, <hi>&amp;c. that God had given him a Name above every name, that at the Name of JESUS every knee ſhould bow</hi> (or be ſubject) <hi>of things in Heaven, and things on Earth, and things under the Earth; and that every tongue ſhould confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the Father.</hi> Which will not be done till he hath received his Kingdom, and ſhall return (as he himſelf ſpeaketh, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.12, 15) and all theſe things can at no other time upon Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-ground be expected but at his ſaid 2d coming, when God ſhall bring again his Son into the world, and ſay, <hi>Let all the Angels of God worſhip him,</hi> Heb. 1.6. and that was alſo foretold, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.7. which whole Pſalm (beginning, <hi>The Lord reigneth, let the Earth rejoyce, &amp;c.</hi>) ſetteth forth prophetically in what a glorious manner Chriſt will come then to ſet up his glorious Kingdom, both by deſtroying his Idolatrous Enemies, and wonderfully delivering and exalting his People (as is obſervable throughout the whole Pſalm,) and this as to the time and order Chriſt ſuccinctly explains, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. ſaying, <hi>the Saints reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi> And accordingly thereunto are all the Promiſes of raiſing again the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> which was fallen, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.11. &amp; <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16. and thoſe for the perpetuity of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom to his ſeed ſo long as the Sun and Moon do endure,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 77, 78, 79.</note> and the like, are all to be interpreted; which will be manifeſt when the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Stone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.33, 34. ſhall become a great Mountain, filling the whole Earth: And this is that <hi>Coming of the Son of man in his Kingdom,</hi> ſpoken of by Chriſt <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.28. of which he ſoon after ſhewed a glymps unto his three Diſciples, <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> at his Transfiguration, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.27. Neither can theſe Texts be juſtly denied to be meant of ſuch a Kingdom of Chriſt to come upon his coming again, nor warrantably be interpreted in any other ſenſe, if the ſaid Texts be ſeriouſly and duly conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> 22. <hi>Obſer.</hi> I have obſerved only three great Earthquakes, ſpoken of in all the ſeries or order of the Book of <hi>Revelation:</hi> And where the Spirit of God calls them <hi>great,</hi> we may expect they will be great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, (For Earthquakes are often ſpoken of beſides theſe great ones). The firſt is upon the opening of the ſixth Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12. when God by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great overturned Satan's Paganiſh Kingdom,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106268:16"/>when five or ſix ſeveral <hi>Caeſars</hi> were ſo potent to oppoſe him,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Fore. runner,</hi> p. 29.</note> and caſt down Satan from his Heaven of Heatheniſh Worſhip into the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9. which was ſpoken of the ſame time which is deſcribed, as a day of Judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. to the Paganiſh Powers (as indeed it was) and there the Spirit of God ſets down an <hi>Ecce</hi> before it; <hi>and Lo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there was a great Earthquake.</hi> The ſecond is, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. at the aſcenſion of the two Witneſſes after their reſurrection, and then the holy Spirit tells us <hi>at the ſame hour there was a great Earthquake,</hi> when the tenth part of the Dition of the City of <hi>Rome</hi> probably will quite fall from it,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Fore runner,</hi> p. 8.</note> where the Witneſſes are to riſe again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this Earthquake we may daily expect: But thirdly, there is another great Earthquake, afterwards ſpoken of to come, which he further illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates much above both the former, and that will be at or about An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt's final deſtruction, at the end of the ſixth Viol, and pouring-out of the ſeventh for the compleating of his ruine, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.17, 18. and then the Spirit of God ſpeaks with a great deal of emphaſis of it, ſaying, v. 18. <hi>And there was a great Earthquake, ſuch as was not ſince Man was upon Earth, ſo mighty an Earthquake and ſo great:</hi> Which ſeems to be further deſcribed in the three following verſes, and ſeems to be at or about the ſame time of <hi>Michael's</hi> ſtanding up to deliver <hi>Daniels</hi> People, when ſuch a time of trouble will be as never was ſince there was a Nation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. and when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of Antichriſt, 2 Theſſ. 2.8. Chriſt <hi>will deſtroy him with the appearance of his coming;</hi> and happily of both, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. latter part of the chapter: And then will <hi>not only the Earth be ſhaken, but alſo the Heavens,</hi> as ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.6, 7, 21. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.26. and as upon good reaſon from ſeveral Scriptures ſeems to be the main drift of them then to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, as <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.16. Which ſhaking of the Earth (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) may ſeem was firſt at that great Earthquake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.12. when God by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great overthrew Paganiſh Idolatry: and may be again by the next great Earthquake now approaching, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. which will alſo begin to ſhake Antichriſtian Idolaters, who are called in this Book, <hi>the men of the Earth:</hi> and the perfecting of that ſhaking is to be at that third and greateſt Earthquake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. when not only the Earth and evil men will be ſhaken, but alſo the Heavens, namely, ſuch Churches as will be then in a degree <hi>reformed Churches;</hi> and thereupon will the new Heavens and new Earth enſue of both reformed Church and State in the whole World, I conceive at the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. &amp; 5.10.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> 23. When the Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> denounceth threatnings againſt the twelve Tribes, the Spirit of God ſeems to guide him (divers times)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106268:16"/>to ſet them down prophetically, as including Prophecies, in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der afterwards to be fulfilled: as is obſervable, <hi>Lev.</hi> 26. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. &amp; 4.30. which he ſaid expreſly ſhould be in the latter dayes; and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. from ver. 1. to 44. See theſe Texts more fully in the <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> pag. 60, 61.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> 24. <hi>Obſer.</hi> The heavy weight of God's wrath upon mankind next after the fall of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> ſeems very obſervable through the firſt great Period of the World until the Flood: for, firſt, good <hi>Abel</hi> (the remoteſt type of Chriſt after <hi>Adam</hi>) being ſlain by his brother; Yet curſed <hi>Cain</hi> was then ſuffered to live to people the World: which fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appears, that in thoſe firſt ages of the World to the Flood, few are recorded or hinted in Scripture, to be faithful or ſaved; and that in a few ſucceſſions amongſt ſuch long-lived perſons, at the end of 1656 years (as the old World's time is computed) it was then for mans wickedneſs and impenitency drowned by an univerſal deluge; ſaving thoſe few in the Ark with <hi>Noah,</hi> and they not all good neither: But afterwards the more remote men lived from the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall, and the nearer they drew on to the 2d <hi>Adam's</hi> firſt coming, the more clearer manifeſtations of God's Grace have appeared in the World: But when Chriſt at his ſaid firſt coming both purchaſed and tendered greater Grace towards both Jews and Gentiles, and that more clearly and largely than ever before: Yet how few (as our Saviour warned) of either ſorts (in compariſon) even in the beſt times, have under that Kingdom of Patience been ſaved! <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.14. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. but eſpecially all that time the Wrath hath lain heavy upon the Jews (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own Curſe upon themſelves and their Poſterity) in a remarkable viſible manner, for above ſixteen hundred years: And ſo ſtrait and narrow hath the way been found to Heaven, in all the times of this Kingdom of Patience even to the Gentile Chriſtians, through all the Heatheniſh, Heretical and Antichriſtian Perſecutions, even to this day; that few (as our Saviour ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.) have ſince found it: But when the times of the Jews free-promiſed mercy (who are alſo yet beloved for their Father's ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) ſhall once appear; the Grace of God by Chriſt will not only be rich and wonderful to them, and to them more eſpecially, But alſo (together with them) to thoſe Gentiles, then to come in at their riſing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.3 <hi>to</hi> 17. with other like places; for then he, the great Meſſiah, will appear wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully glorious, in reſpect of both, (then) made one in him (<hi>Joh.</hi> 10.16.) the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> and that not only in the tenders of his Grace (as formerly to the Jews before Chriſt's birth) and afterwards towards all in the firſt preaching of the Goſpel; but alſo (then) his glorious Grace
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106268:17"/>will appear in the power and efficacy thereof abundantly, in his pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-forth his Grace and Spirit upon them both, and cauſing them to walk in his wayes according to his promiſes, <hi>Ezek,</hi> 36. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 1 <hi>to</hi> 11. And likewiſe then he will ſhew himſelf in his Perſon, more powerful to ſave his Saints, and ſubdue his Enemies, than the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was weak and ſinful in ruining his natural race, and giving all Enemies advantage againſt all God's Choſen People till that time: that as <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74. they ſhall (then) be delivered from thoſe Enemies, and the hands of all that hate them, to ſerve him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for from that time of his Kingdom of Power neither Enemies temporal or ſpiritual ſhall have thenceforward any advantage or power to hurt the Saints (though once they will attempt it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.8, 9.) So that what the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> loſt for himſelf and his poſterity ſo fooliſhly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſhamefully; the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> will (then) happily manifeſt he hath again regained, even to his ſpiritual ſeed on Earth moſt holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, powerfully and gloriouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> 25. <hi>Obſer.</hi> Our Saviour aſcended from Mount <hi>Olivet, Acts</hi> 1.12. and was then taken out of his Diſciples ſight by a cloud, ver. 12. and <hi>he ſhall ſo come again in the clouds,</hi> (ſaid the Angels) v. 11. as is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Mark</hi> 13.26. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. and it ſeems probable, that Propbecy of his feet ſtanding upon Mount <hi>Olivet</hi> at that time, when he will at his coming again manifeſt himſelf to the Jews for their National Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> is of opinion, will then ſpeak to them) will then have its fulfilling, <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.4. which chapter ſets forth many things then to be accompliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> 26. The Prophet <hi>Malachi</hi> ſpeaks of two harbingers or forerunners of Chriſt at his firſt and ſecond coming. The firſt was <hi>John Baptiſt, Mal.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Behold, I ſend my Meſſenger before thy face, &amp;c.</hi> which was applied by the Angel, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.76. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.9, 10. ſhewing in what ſenſe he was called <hi>Elias</hi> by the Angel here, and by our Saviour afterwards, as <hi>Luke</hi> 1.17. namely in the Spirit and Power of <hi>Elias;</hi> and our Saviour ſpeaketh of both <hi>Eliaſes</hi> together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.11, 12. and what the turning of fathers to the children may be, ſee <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.14. The other harbinger or forerunner which <hi>Malachi</hi> ſpeaks of, chap. 4.5, 6. to be before the great and dreadful Day of the Lord come, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhall be <hi>Elias</hi> the Tiſhbite, or <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> raiſed again from the dead (as ſeveral of the Ancients have ſeverally conceived) or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhall be one at that time to be ſent (as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was) in the Spirit and Power of <hi>Elias</hi> at his coming again, as the Angel before expounded concerning <hi>John Baptiſt, Luk.</hi> 1.17. I will not contend: But this I aſſuredly believe, that that Meſſenger to be ſent before
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106268:17"/>Chriſt at his ſecond coming, ſpoken of <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.5, 6. ſhall then alſo be ſpirited and fitly qualified for ſo great a work, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> 27. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> When the ſtamp of the Primitive times, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of the verſe, <hi>[Many ſhall run to and fro,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 63, 64.</note> and knowledge ſhall be encreaſed:]</hi> and then Antichriſt's <hi>time, times, and the dividing of a time,</hi> v. 5, 6, 7. ſet forth myſtically and very darkly to <hi>Daniel,</hi> being things that concerned not the Jews (directly) but the Gentile Chriſtians in both thoſe times, being to come a long time after; He thereupon ſaid; v. 8. <hi>Though I heard, yet I underſtood not,</hi> though in part expounded to him before by the Angel, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.24, 25. But of what concerned his People the Jews both before and after, he had further ſuch marks ſet down in the following part of the chapter, that were like in time to come to be more diſcernable by them, ver. 10, 11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as mainly concerned themſelves in the time of the end, chap. 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but were to be ſhut up till then, v. 4, 9. See <hi>Abridgment on Dan.</hi> 12.4, 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> 28. <hi>Obſer.</hi> Chriſt's eminent execution of his three great Offices in reſpect of his Univerſal Church in the three great Periods of the World, is very obſervable in Scripture and Providence: Firſt, of ſuch his Prophetical Office under the Old Teſtament, by his Spirit of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Revelation. Secondly, of ſuch his Prieſtly Office under the New Teſtament, both by his Sacrifice and Interceſſion, unto his coming again by his Spirit of Grace and Truth. Thirdly, in his emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Kingly Office in his Thouſand years Reign, beginning when he ſhall begin to judge quick and dead, at his Appearance, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and continuing to the looſing of Satan after he hath been bound &amp; ſealed up in the bottomleſs-pit the ſaid thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. to be manifeſt (then) by his Spirit of Power and Dominion. See theſe largely conſidered in ſeventeen <hi>Theſes,</hi> with Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in the <hi>Forerunner,</hi> pag. 12, 13. and confirmed by Arguments in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 33, 34.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> 29. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> The Spirit of God ſeems frequently to joyn matters of the latter times together, which will be fulfilled at a great diſtance, and particularly concerning the two Reſurrections, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and even the whole Doctrine of the Reſurrection (almoſt) (as we noted in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 102. and elſewhere) was made known by degrees, and ſo the two Seſſions of the great day of Judgment, <hi>vide Obſer.</hi> 2. But as we here obſerve, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſets three great things down together, namely, Chriſt's Reſurrection as the firſt fruits of the Reſurrection of the Juſt, at the ſaid firſt Reſurrection, or at his ſecond coming, which is like to be about 1700 years after, and then cometh the end, which according as Chriſt hath revealed, will be above a thouſand years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106268:18"/>his ſecond coming, and at his third. So that mark of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4. to wit <hi>[Many ſhall run to and fro, and knowledge ſhall be encreaſed]</hi> divers hundreds of years before Antichriſt's <hi>time, times, and the dividing of a time:</hi> which are ſet forth in a wonderfull Viſion of Chriſt (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. likewiſe) in the three next verſes, 5, 6, 7. which contain 1260 years more. So three Queſtions are propounded by Chriſt's Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. of the ſigns of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction, and of his coming again or returning (as he called it before, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.12.) and of the end of the World. To all our Saviour anſwers, but much of the neareſt, and gives divers ſigns of his ſecond coming in the clouds of Heaven, which he ſpeaks of, ver. 30. but cloſely there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto adjoyns what ſhould be done at his third coming, v. 31. which was not to be ſo much revealed (ſaving myſtically afterwards in the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi>) which was in reſpect thereof to be the true Key to open in after-times the ſpiritual Cabinet of divers (otherwiſe) myſtical Texts, darkly ſet down by Chriſt and his holy Spirit, in other places of Scripture to the like purpoſe: (and ſo to be ſuch a Key for other things) See the like, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31. ſpeaks in part of his ſecond coming; and in the other part of that verſe, and ver. 32. he ſpeaks of what ſhall be done at his third coming, largely expounded ſo by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, to the end of the chapter. So again St. <hi>Paul</hi> in 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> and chap. 4.14. he ſpeaks of Chriſt's ſecond coming, when Chriſt will bring all his Saints, and all that (then) ſhall ſleep in Jeſus, with him: but in ver. 16. he ſpeaks of his laſt coming, as alſo expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt in the ſaid place. Alſo again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23. the Apoſtle plainly ſpeaks of his ſecond coming, and ver. 52. ſets down divers things to be done at Chriſts coming at the laſt Seſſion of Judgment and laſt Reſurrection: And becauſe it appears God would have theſe things concerning the laſt times of the World to be ſo darkly deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the moſt part, and in myſteries in the <hi>Revelation.</hi> Hence it hath come to paſs, that ſuch imperfect and miſtaken apprehenſions have for the moſt part been entertained by all ſorts of men; and without ſome ſpecial guidance of God's Spirit could not (probably) be otherwiſe found out, who himſelf is ſaid to have opened the Diſciples under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding after his Reſurrection, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.45. that they might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Scriptures: but as many then which heard them neither believed nor regarded what they taught; and thoſe matters of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by Jeſus Chriſt crucified, riſen and aſcended, were hidden from moſt mens eyes; ſo it is to be expected it will be (as we are fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned) with moſt men in reſpect of Chriſt's deſcending or coming again the ſecond time, by ſtumbling at ſuch Scriptures that concern it
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106268:18"/>on one prejudice or miſtake or other. It concerns thoſe therefore that will approve themſelves wiſe, to be wary in ſuch matters, of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them by ſlightly, which ſuch as rightly ſhall receive and own, are like to find much ſweetnes and benefit by them, being ſuch as duely ſearch into them: For Chriſts bleſſing, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.3. will not be void or vain, ſay vain men what they can, or wicked men and devils act what they can to the contrary. See <hi>Diſcovery of his Second and Third coming, next after the Parallels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> 30. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That of <hi>Daniel,</hi> 12.2, 3. is ſpecially meant of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Reſurrection of the <hi>Jews,</hi> from their bondage and diſperſion, the time of which is afterwards ſet down, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. which (in a viſion of the dry bones, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. is ſhewed to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) is many wayes evident; (as afterwards follows) and ſo that Reſurrection was to be carried on to the end of the fourty five years, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. afterwards; when Chriſt will fully deliver them both temporally and ſpiritually, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. Many arguments might be raiſed from the words to this purpoſe, and from the time wherein the things are to be fulfilled, according both to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and <hi>Daniel:</hi> When it is ſaid, <hi>Many ſhall ariſe,</hi> not all. And again it is ſaid, <hi>They ſhall be turned unto righteouſneſs,</hi> that is, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt; which was contrary to the Legal righteouſneſs, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> before ſought after. Again ſome ariſe to ſhame and contempt at that time, that is, by revolting from the faithful <hi>Jewes</hi> (then) by fears, or hopes, or threatnings, or the like, from the enemy; and ſo fall into ſhame and perpetual contempt both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, ſpiritually, and (conſequently) eternally. It is obſervable that the Spirit of God ſometimes ſetteth down Myſteries of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the order they are to be fulfilled, in the reſemblance of a day of Judgment, as here; and ſometimes though ſuch things be done long before the end of the world; as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>When the ſixth ſeal was opened,</hi> in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, which is above one thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years ago, and yet there deſcribed as a day of Judgement, but yet it was but a particular one for that time; but no Judgement ſaid then to be ſet, nor Books opened, and quick and dead both Judged, as will be at Chriſts ſecond and third Comings; as was ſaid in our ſecond large <hi>Obſervation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> 31. <hi>Obſerv.</hi> The harmoniouſneſs and uniform agreement of theſe divine Truths, reſpecting the Reign of Chriſt the thouſand years (touched (at leaſt briefly) in divers of the preceding Obſervations) ſhewes them to come from God, and their agreeing with the divine Oracles of the holy Spirit, ſcattered in all parts of the ſacred Scriptures (as in many particulars have been here already ſet down, and as we may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106268:19"/>afterwards point out, or at leaſt briefly hint at) As in the two Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the great Day of Judgment: with the four particulars proper to the day of Judgement. <hi>Firſt,</hi> In both, the <hi>Judgement is</hi> ſaid to be <hi>ſet. Secondly,</hi> In both, <hi>The Books are</hi> ſaid to be <hi>opened. Thirdly,</hi> In both, firſt the <hi>quick:</hi> And <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In both, laſt the <hi>dead are judged.</hi> See the large ſecond Obſervation to theſe purpoſes. Again, theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are ſuitable to the ſecond perſonal coming of Chriſt, to be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after at the beginning, and after the little ſpace, when the thouſand years ſhall be ended. See them at large in the <hi>Plain Diſcovery after the Parallels.</hi> At the firſt Chriſt removes the hinderers and oppoſers of his reigning in the World, towards whom God had ſhewed long Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience all the time of Chriſts ſitting at his right hand; and his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants patience had been all along exerciſed by them: Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding by their Faith and Patience all along, that Kingdom of Patience (now almoſt at an end) have inherited the Promiſes hitherto, and ſtill ſhall do through the thouſand years: But <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. at the end of Chriſts ſitting at Gods right hand in Heaven, he will begin to make his foes his foot-ſtool; by deſtroying the firſt <hi>Gog and Magog,</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> by a complication of Judgments; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, <hi>&amp;</hi> 39. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.18. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. with <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. And binding Satan. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.1, 2, 3. See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. <hi>Then God will ſet his King upon his holy hill of Sion,</hi> Pſal. 2. and ſo perform the ſure mercies to <hi>David</hi> for ever, and that before himſelf: for all which it is plainly recorded (as is to be well obſerved, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. in a great part of that <hi>Chapter</hi>) See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 21. <hi>And then he will make every knee to bow to him in Heaven, and Earth, and under the Earth,</hi> Phil. 2. <hi>Having given him a Name above every Name,</hi> &amp;c. For then thoſe in Heaven, Angels and Saints, come with him into the World, when God ſhall bring his Son the ſecond time into it; as <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. which was propheſied of by <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 97. throughout, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Scriptures. <hi>Vide Irenicon,</hi> from <hi>pag.</hi> 42, to <hi>pag.</hi> 88. And then, <hi>all ſuch as ſleep in Jeſus will God bring with him,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.14. See <hi>Obſer.</hi> 21. <hi>And he will</hi> (then bodily) <hi>begin to reward his Servants the Prophets, and his Saints,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 11.18. <hi>by that bleſſed firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> Rev. 20.6. and (probably) as they were eminent in grace, or ſufferings, or both, ſo much the ſooner. And in Earth, the <hi>Jews</hi> will then become, upon a miraculous Call and Converſion, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zealous and bleſſed People, <hi>being beloved for their Fathers ſake,</hi> Rom. 11. See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 15. The heathen <hi>Gentiles</hi> will earneſtly (then) ſeek Chriſts face and favour; and even make uſe (then) of the <hi>Jews</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to procure Chriſts favour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The very infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106268:19"/>creatures then will be freed from their bondage of co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uption, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. For there ſhall be no wicked men, that ſhall then dare to abuſe them, or tyrannize over them as formerly. See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 21. yea even ſuch wicked men as will then be ſpared, proving hypocrites (as is probable) will themſelves be made ſlaves then, as diverſe Scriptures ſeem to ſpeak. For as ſin brought alwayes with it a Spiritual ſlavery before; ſo it is like always remarkably to add an outward viſible ſlavery, to all evil men in the world then: But thoſe Creatures will be matter of Gods praiſe to the Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chriſt will then delegate the power and management of that his Kingdom to the Saints, for him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18, 22, 27. even that Kingdom he received of the Father, and which he gave to them (as he ſpeaks) and that they may rule for him, <hi>v.</hi> 27. <hi>Firſt,</hi> to the firſt raiſed Saints, and then to other eminent Saints in the natural life; as his enemies which he came to deſtroy, had ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt him before, which will be the juſt reaſon and cauſe of their ruine then, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27.</p>
            <p>The Covenant and Mercies to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſworn to them perſonally, and yet never perſonally perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in reſpect of their enjoying the Land of <hi>Canaan:</hi> neither had their natural Seed that Land, as it was made ſure to that one ſeed, Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. for ever, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.21. and that as the dayes of heaven upon the earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 15. But it ſhall be then accordingly performed as it was promiſed and ſworn. As likewiſe the Oath to <hi>David</hi> in <hi>David's</hi> Seed, and Saviour, and Antitype, to reign ſo long as the Sun and Moon ſhall endure. See <hi>Irenicon, pag.</hi> 77, to <hi>pag.</hi> 80. And <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 21. So of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> called, <hi>Jehova Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Ezek.</hi> 48. <hi>ult.</hi> which is ſaid, <hi>to come down from God out of Heaven, Rev.</hi> 21. <hi>where the Tabernacle of God, is ſaid to be with men.</hi> See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. And, <hi>the new Heavens and new Earth.</hi> See <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 22. later end; with divers other Contemporaries for that thouſand years, as the Tree of Life and pure River. See <hi>Iren. pag.</hi> 30. whereby the bleſſed, gracious and glorious ſtate of all things then are decyphred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe and the like points of Doctrine were enlarged upon, and ſitly placed in their due order of accompliſhment, as the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſet them forth, with ſuch Rational and Scriptural Illuſtrations, as are beſt ſuitable to their natures amongſt themſelves, and in their ſweet harmony, with all other divine Truths, there ſet down; I doubt not but when once God ſhall give any ſorts of men ſuch Faith, as to receive theſe things upon the divine authority of his Word, they will appear both comfortable and excellent, and prove forcible to ſuch true Believers for increaſe of ſanctification, above what they received
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106268:20"/>before, and make to them (as I have found by experience) many parts of holy Scripture more clear and ſweet, and many wayes more uſeful, than otherwiſe they can be to them; whereas, without theſe Doctrines, I find I did not, nor could ever have rightly underſtood or known them; namely, what ſuch Texts of Scriptures, reſpecting theſe and the like Doctrines, do chiefly mean or drive at; and I believe many others by degrees may find the like experience thereof in time.</p>
            <p>But I am now many wayes reſtrained from enlarging therein, and therefore only at preſent, hint theſe things to believing Chriſtians in ſuch reſpects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>To Glory's God all Glory's due for aye:</l>
                     <l>To Him alone, this Due, let all his pay.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="representation">
            <head>A brief repreſentation of the Doctrine of Chriſts Kingdom of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to come upon Earth, together with an endeavour to remove unjuſt prejudices from it: To prevent the great ſin and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being aſhamed of Chriſt and his Truth, even that great Truth of his Kingdom, <hi>Joh. 18.37.</hi> Before a ſinful and an adulterous generation: of both which we are warned. <hi>Mat. 8.38.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>True Chriſtian Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE great and precious Truths reſpecting Chriſt Jeſus our Saviours glorious appearance to deſtroy Antichriſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Body of the Jewiſh Nation, to begin his glorious Reign with his raiſed Saints on Earth for a thouſand years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all this probably ſhortly to be manifeſt in the World, which God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to diſcover unto me a poor weak and an unworthy inſtrument, in ſuch remarkable wayes as he hath led me, according to his Word, and by the guidance and operation of his holy Spirit, and hath ſo ſtrongly evidenced to my own ſoul (and which hath been by ſundry learned men and judicious Chriſtians acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged) and I doubt not will be owned more and more, I am well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red are of ſo high concernment, both for the glory of God and our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106268:20"/>Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and for the edification and comfort of his People in the laſt times, that I ſhall be ready by his Grace upon all fitting occaſions, to warn all ſuch as truly fear God, to take heed either of ſlighting or rejecting of them; for though they are of that nature that God hath in his moſt wiſe counſel reſerved to be more eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known for his true Churches benefit in theſe laſt dayes, when his ancient People the Jews are ſhortly to be converted unto Chriſt their Saviour (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) <hi>and all Iſrael ſhall be ſaved;</hi> that even as the Myſtery of the Gentiles Converſion was hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to the Jews, and even, for a time, to the Apoſtles themſelves, when it was to take place, until by Miracles, Word, Spirit, and Viſions, they were powerfully taught to acknowledge it: So theirs is like in great part to be hid to the Gentiles. And as Antichriſt was to come to be revealed to reign, to be conſumed with the breath of Chriſt's mouth, uttered by his Witneſſes, but all to be fulfilled in a great Myſtery all along to the moſt in the World, ſaving unto ſome few perſons and places, unto whom by degrees God in ſpecial wayes of mercy hath been pleaſed from time to time to manifeſt theſe things; and yet (I ſay) but by degrees (for the accompliſhment of God's Myſteries) have in all times been very wonderful, and above mens reach ordinarily to diſcover. And as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was greatly honoured and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Jewiſh Rulers and learned Rabbies of his time, whilſt he perſecuted the Chriſtian Faith, yet when afterward he preached that Goſpel of <hi>Chriſt crucified,</hi> and that unto the Gentiles, was as much by thoſe Jews perſecuted and oppoſed himſelf, and by all of their way: ſo in a degree may it be expected of ſuch as God manifeſteth ſuch things unto, as he will accompliſh <hi>in the end of the dayes</hi> (as <hi>Daniel's</hi> phraſe is) which ſhall appear to be againſt the intereſt of men in the world, or above the ordinary ſtrain of the times, that many (though not all) will ſlight and oppoſe them, even until God fulfils them; and ſuch their ſlighting and oppoſing is like to be (as to the Jews of old) the occaſion of ſuch his fulfilling of them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. But then many ſuch, <hi>will they, nill they,</hi> muſt give glory to God, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.13. for ſo it pleaſeth God uſually to hide great things from the wiſe and prudent, and to reveal them unto babes, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.21.</p>
            <p>But to prevent and remove prejudices:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt then,</hi> Let all ſerious Chriſtian Spirits take notice that in thoſe two firſt Books I have endeavoured to vindicate the true Doctrine of Chriſt's Kingdom on Earth to come, from thoſe unjuſt aſperſions of Diſloyalty to Kings and Magiſtrates, as moſt oppoſit thereunto; which though haply it hath been unpleaſing to ſome, yet otherwiſe I had
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106268:21"/>not therein ſo approved my ſelf unto God, ſatisfied mine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, done right to many ſorts of men, nor to the Doctrine which I have been taught (as I ſaid before;) and this may three times be ſeen in the ſaid Books; in the firſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 15. ſomewhat largely; and <hi>pag.</hi> 41 &amp; 42. reckoning ſuch deluſions among Satans Vials on Chriſt's Kingdom: and in the ſecond Book, in the <hi>Preface</hi> of it, towards the end of the ſecond leaf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let all ſuch obſerve, that thoſe things which (as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) I have by God's ſpecial guidance publiſhed, are (for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) nothing but the true Scriptural explications of the old Articles of the Faith (as Learned-men had before manifeſted from the beſt Antiquity) and owned in great part in the moſt pure Primitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times; But yet, upon a better ground for us, are now to be owned from the moſt pure and infallible Word of Truth, that <hi>more ſure Word of Prophecy</hi> (as 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19.) whereunto all Chriſtians are bound to take heed. For as we profeſs to believe that Jeſus Chriſt will come from the right hand of the Father to judge the quick and the dead, and likewiſe to believe the Reſurrection of the Juſt, and the Life of the World to come, (as the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, according to <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.) And how theſe things ſhall be fulfilled, our Saviour (who beſt knew) hath himſelf inſtructed his Church (together with the time when, in ſome good meaſure, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18.) at his glorious appearing, both begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to judge the quick, then by deſtroying of them that deſtroyed the Earth, (<hi>i.e.</hi> Antichriſt and his Accomplices) with the appearance of his coming, as 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. and 2dly, by giving reward unto his Servants the Prophets, and unto his Saints, and to all that fear his Name both ſmall and great; which is then to be done in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Juſt, as is further explained, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5, 6. when alſo begins the Reign of the Saints with Chriſt on Earth the ſaid thouſand years, while Satan alſo ſhall be bound, as ver. 1, 2, 3. du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time our Saviour ſhews that the Apoſtles ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Mat.</hi> 19.28. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which Period he more fully explains himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29. <hi>I appoint unto you a Kingdom, as my Father hath appointed unto me;</hi> where his Throne muſt be diſtinct from his Fathers, where he ſate on his right hand in Heaven, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. is clearly explained: which Kingdom, appointed to him by his Father, the Apoſtle ſhews, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. at the end the ſame ſhall be delivered again to his Father, when ends the ſaid Kingdom that the Father had appointed to him with his Saints on Earth, which began at his beginning to judge the quick and the dead, at his firſt appearing (as was ſhewed) which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106268:21"/>all the ſaid thouſand years, and the finiſhing of the Judgment of the Juſt and Wicked, concerning which there are ſo abundant and evident proofs in Scripture that (when Antichriſtian prejudices ſhall once be removed, even that ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, as 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.3. which ſuch do not in the Apoſtles ſenſe, that acknowledg not the fulfilling of all Chriſt's Offices in their ſeaſons, as the Scripture holds them out, till his Mediatorſhip be conſummate, which the ſpirit of Antichriſt hath all along oppoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then (I ſay) I confidently believe thoſe glorious Truths will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently be manifeſt and received in the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Now for the Subjects of that Kingdom of Chriſt on Earth (that we may give a little further taſte of the Doctrine thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we proceed to the removal of the prejudices againſt it) They will be firſt the Body of the Nation of the Jews, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the moſt part miraculouſly converted upon Chriſt's glorious appearance, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably his ſpeaking to them (as in that pattern of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of many Jews, about three hundred years after Chriſt, as in Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>'s Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi>'s ſecond Letter) See <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10, 11. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. &amp; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. with many other Texts of Scripture. 2dly. Another ſort of ſubjects then, will be, Converted Heathen Gentiles then to come in, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.5, 6, <hi>&amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 19. who ſhall be then Chriſt's <hi>Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the Earth his Poſſeſſion,</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.8. which the Apoſtle reckons the greateſt riches of the Gentiles. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12. <hi>If the caſting off the Jews was the riches of the Gentiles, how much more their fulneſs!</hi> And afterwards, v. 25. he reveals it as a Myſtery (to humble us Gentiles in the mean time) <hi>that blindneſs was in part happened to the Jews, until a firſt fulneſs of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles was come in:</hi> which our Saviour expreſſeth, by the fulfilling of the times of the Gentiles, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.24. for ſo long was the Jews cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and miſerable Captivity to endure from <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction, as is evident from the context. 3dly. Chriſt's chief and beſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or Aſſeſſors and Deputies then in that his Kingdom, will be the bleſſed raiſed Saints in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> come down from God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. who is ſaid to be the Maker and Builder of that City, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16. which are they, our Saviour ſaith, that are counted worthy of that World, and the Reſurrection of the Juſt, called there alſo <hi>the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Reſurrection,</hi> Luk. 20.35, 36. even in that <hi>habitable World,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. And at that time when God brings his Son again into the World, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. Where thoſe which God gave him before, ſhall ſee his own Glory given him, as Mediator, by the Father, as a manifeſtation of his eternal love to him, who he knew
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106268:22"/>would perfectly fulfill that Office; and (therefore in his laſt Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Will) he bequeatheth it to them in the preſence of his Father and his Diſciples, ſaying, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will that they, &amp;c.</hi> Obſerve well both the words and the context, they are very weighty, all full to this purpoſe, that thoſe raiſed Saints ſhall there be where Chriſt is in his own Kingdom, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. there beholding his Glory, and many other Texts to the like purpoſe. Conſider in the Books, wherein many other excellent and ſweet points of Chriſtian Doctrine to ſerious ſpirits may be obſervable bordering upon theſe, which to ſuch may (by God's Grace) be exceeding available to promote Grace and Piety, and that from a great advantage above what uſually hath been taught, or is yet expected by moſt Chriſtians, namely, from the weighty conſideration of the happineſs of the whole man both in ſoul and body together, and that upon Earth, where thoſe Saints were formerly deſpiſed and ſuffered, when their enemies ſhall not live in body, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.14. but they ſhall live with Chriſt in a triumphant ſtate of Glory, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. and that above a thouſand years ſooner than is ordinarily expected; and this happy eſtate will be a ſure entrance into the poſſeſſion of eternal bleſſedneſs in the higheſt Heavens. Men uſe too greatly to prize, and very dearly purchaſe (many times with the loſs of their precious ſouls) their earthly falſly ſuppoſed perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuities; and when they have done all, know not that they or their heirs ſhall poſſeſs (I will not ſay enjoy them) for a thouſand dayes on Earth; but ſuppoſe a lawful acquired purchaſe, and left ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily with the greateſt hope of bleſſing by a Godly Parent to a gracious Chriſtian Poſterity, yet how ſoon do ſucceſſions many times here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, and in ſome few hundreds of years how are Eſtates and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions turned up-ſide down, as ſacred and other Hiſtories abundantly evidence! and the beſt mens beſt eſtate is here full of evil as well as good, bitter ſweets at the beſt; yea, they and every <hi>man in his beſt eſtate is altogether vanity,</hi> Pſal. 39. And doth Chriſt by his own pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar teaching (and his evidence muſt needs be beſt) aſſure his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants he hath procured and appointed unto them not a ſmall pittance, but a Kingdom, and one that cannot be ſhaken; not for a life here, or a few ſucceſſions, but for <hi>a thouſand years on Earth;</hi> free not only from outward enemies, but in the judgment of the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from far worſe, <hi>ſcil.</hi> from Sin and Satan, with all their retinue, Shame, Sorrow, Death, Hell, with all that black Regiment that guards them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On the other hand; What bruitiſh madneſs do wiſe men reckon ſuch to be poſſeſſed with that caſt away a great Eſtate with the caſting of a Dye, or by any other ſinful earthly frenzy? but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106268:22"/>what is it for any worldly vanity, with a curſe hereunto entailed, and ſometimes, purſuing it cloſe at the heels, to caſt away a ſure Chriſtian Intereſt in ſuch a Kingdom, as Chriſt's is ſure to be on earth; ſo glorious, ſo ſatisfying (as every condition of the faithful after death is ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully) ſo ſecure, every way bleſſed in what they enjoy at that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod, and in what they know they ſhall enjoy to all eternity! For as evil men are made to know all the degrees of their curſed eſtate, both of ſoul and body; likewiſe to come to their exceeding horror, from the very moment of their death, when their Conſcience being let looſe, is their accuſer, witneſs, judge, executioner and continual tormentor; ſo godly men appear to know from the very moment of their departure hence, every happy condition they are to paſs through to eternity: therefore of this ſtate, ſaid the repreſentatives, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. almoſt one thouſand ſix hundred years ago, <hi>we ſhall reign upon earth;</hi> ſo that on the one hand, upon this ſaid great advantage, Chriſtians may be ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the Apoſtles argument <hi>(a fortiori)</hi> more ſtrongly, as the good is ſo great and near approaching: wherefore, <hi>Beloved brethren, ſince theſe things are ſo, what manner of men ought we to be, in all holy manner of converſation?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, in reſpect of evil men <hi>(a fortiori)</hi> they will not only loſe ſuch happineſs, which they wil not now believe, but they will preſently know they have loſt it, and that it will from thenceforth be irrecoverable; and which ever will make them miſerable, they will find they were taken hence in wrath, from the tenders of mercy which they had, &amp; ſhal never have tenders thereof again made before Chriſt's ſecond coming, or at his coming, nor after the laſt reſurrection: ſo that whether thus taken away in particular-diſpleaſure, or in the common deſtruction of the wicked, they will throughly know each miſerable eſtate which ſhall abode them, privatively, poſitively, as well their <hi>poenam damni,</hi> as <hi>poenam ſenſus;</hi> as well what they have irreparably loſt, as what in every eſtate to eternity will be inflicted upon them.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>But here by the way is one great Queſtion; How will this Doctrine be proved; for many great and learned men do not aſſent to it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether any Doctrine that is founded evidently and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on Gods Word, is owned by learned men, or eminent men in the world, will not be the queſtion at laſt, <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> at leaſt if thou hadſt pauſedly read with due attention, or heard the ſound of ſuch Doctrine of Chriſt, thou oughteſt to ſearch, whether thoſe things are ſo. Men on both parts are to be heard more in regard of their Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture evidence, for what they affirm, than in any other regard, in the things of God and the ſalvation and happineſs of ſouls. But for this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106268:23"/>Doctrine, it hath been, and is abundantly proved, if men would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſeek information, and ſo as never will be refelled; and I doubt not but will more and more with many of Gods People be owned and improved; but it will in this be found (as in all other branches of Chriſtian Faith) it muſt be Gods Spirit muſt perſwade men to believe it, though they know it, for none can believe what they know not; therefore it will neceſſarily follow, when they have the knowledge of it, they muſt earneſtly pray, and meditate, and conſider, and importune the Father of Mercies, to know in this reſpect his will; yea, and though they be reckoned wiſe and prudent, and learned too in ſuch matters, they muſt go to Chriſt as babes, to be taught by his Spirit: Parts, Learning, Authority of men, may work conviction, but cannot perſwade men to own and apply unto themſelves any divine and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious truths of God in Scripture, for the benefit of his Church. And therefore (Chriſtian) if this Doctrine held out to thee be of God, thou art bound carefully and diligently to enquire after it, for if thou beeſt faithful, it is part of thine inheritance, and exceeding uſeful and needful for thee too in the laſt dayes, that the evil conſequences of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting of it, may not inevitably fall upon thee. On the other hand, there are degrees of glory to be obtained of the Saints, <hi>For one ſtar differeth from another ſtar in glory.</hi> For any through the rejecting of ſuch Doctrine of the Goſpel, but to loſe the happineſs, in the more ſpeedy reſurrection of the Juſt ſome few hundreds of years, may well be deemed a great loſs. And as the Ancients judged there will be <hi>(mora)</hi> a deferring of ſome (probably) upon ſuch an account, how ſhould men therefore ſeek to be ſtrengthened in all kind of Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But thoſe Scriptures have been otherwiſe interpreted by many able and good men in an other ſence, only for ſpiritual conſolation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That many able and good men have ſo underſtood them, hath been becauſe of the unjuſt ſcandals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that a long time have been caſt upon this Doctrine of Truth by the ſubtilty of Satan and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of men, or at leaſt for want of diſcovery; but how weakly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiently ſome who might of later times have had more light ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, have gone about to evade the Truth, may to a diſcerning impartial eye, eaſily appear; that while they have gain-ſaid the Truth, have many times laid down evident proofs and confirmations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſo that their own Writings might ſufficiently manifeſt their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes; beſides, God hath raiſed many able and judicious perſons of later times, that have both vindicated theſe Truths, and ſufficiently anſwered what by others (though otherwiſe men of good account)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106268:23"/>have unwarrantably been ſet down to the contrary, as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But ſome may happily ſay, they are ſatisfied with the knowledge of what is and hath been accounted neceſſary to ſalvation, and think it not needful to trouble themſelves with things dark and myſterious, though they be truths,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As God hath works to fulfil in all Ages of his Church, ſo hath he needful Truths to be owned and believed in ſeveral conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and eſtates his People are to paſs thorow in this world; but theſe great Truths concerning the right underſtanding of what God doth and is about to accompliſh in theſe laſt times, are now more in their proper ſeaſon (as was ſaid) are his more diſtinct and clear explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſome Articles of Chriſtian Faith; and though the Scriptures, however they have been plentiful, yet have formerly of old been more dark in ſetting them down (according to the divine wiſdom and pleaſure of the incomprehenſible God) and yet in much grace to his true Church, in theſe laſt times, hath made them very evident, that we may by no means conceive thoſe plentiful portions of ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, reſpecting theſe things, are now in their ſeaſon to be overlooked; ſince God hath ſuch excellent ends in revealing them to his People, both for his &amp; our Saviours glory, and his Peoples ſeaſonable and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful conſolation; for there is no word of Grace written for believing ſouls, but they know it in its due ſeaſon and uſe, to be more of worth than all the world: and therefore this general charge Wiſdom gives her Children, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.4. <hi>To ſeek her as ſilver, and ſearch for her as hid treaſures;</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>whereby they may underſtand the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God;</hi> with many like encouragements. And our Saviour, the wiſdom of the Father, enjoyneth men for ſeaſonable Truths, in his Life-time, to ſearch the Scriptures (then) the ſame charge lies upon all his People now, which whoſo endeavours faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, ſhall find his bleſſing accordingly in ſo doing; and then myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries before, are no longer myſteries to them to whom God reveals them for the good of others.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But ſuch as ſeek into ſuch Myſteries do often miſtake and differ one from the other, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The great things of God are ſometimes ſo high that he is pleaſed but to reveal them by degrees, and in their proper ſeaſons; yet every degree (of ſuch he imployes to ſeek into them) really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes his end, and when his time is come, either by ſearching, or revelation, or both (or as he pleaſeth) he makes them known; and when they are ſo they are highly to be prized, and duly to be impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106268:24"/>and though in ſome things leſs eſſential ſome miſtakes may be amongſt ſome good men, and differences of apprehenſions, yet ſtill by ſuch ſearching, the Word will reſolve them. I muſt acknowledge to God's glory, before men and Angels, I have to my own great ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction found the experience thereof, which I have therefore in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſet down ſincerely and faithfully, with the ſenſe of mine own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for other mens profit and advantage, (though the intent of that Treatiſe (called <hi>The Irenicon</hi>) was to prove ſuch a Kingdom of Chriſt was to come:) yet, as I found a remarkable hand of God upon me, many wayes leading me to diſcern and acknowledge a perſonal appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt, after I had laid down ſome reaſons of my former ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of a myſtical, which I likewiſe ſufficiently anſwered, ſo, as may make much for the advantage of ſuch as will duly weigh that work of God upon me, by whom with my ſeeking (with ſmall help of men) I deſired to be guided ſo, as ever to have an eye and an ear open to the directions of his Word and Spirit, of the proceedings, wherein I have endeavoured in ſundry places, on ſeveral occaſions, to give an account advantagious to ſerious Chriſtian ſouls, and greater than if it had been otherwiſe, as upon ſundry conſiderations might be made to appear; and though in ſuch ſubjects (for divers reaſons) men that write of them cannot well be much in explications and applications, leſt they be too voluminous, in laying down the principles and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, as the foundation of them, in the firſt place neceſſary, yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards it will be eaſie (by God's aſſiſtance) for all ſorts of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſtians to do it for their own benefit, and the edification of others. And to which purpoſe I ſhall likewiſe, by God's Grace, be ready upon any call of his to approve my ſelf to all mens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the clearing and improving of ſuch needful Truths, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my meaſure, and as he may give me opportunity, (which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I conceive may be the chief work remaining to me in this world) though haply they may find reſiſtance from Satan, the end of whoſe Kingdom they hold out; or from ſeveral ſorts of men, either upon prejudice or want of ſearching and trying them by the Scriptures, or from ſome evil diſpoſition of ſpirit or other, or worldly engagements to the contrary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it hath uſually been with the Witneſſings of other Truths of God in their ſeaſons: but this is the comfort in ſuch caſe, Truth ſhall prevail, and Gods Word ſhall ſtand when all is done; for he that is with ſuch as witneſs for it, is Almighty, and will ſuffer no Truth of his utterly to fall to the ground (though for a time it may ſuffer an eclypſe) but in the mean time the work of his Witneſſes is with him their Lord, and their labour with their God. And as no
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106268:24"/>Truth of God is in its ſeaſon to be rejected, ſo concerning theſe there ſeems to be leſs reaſon in this regard; becauſe the Spirit of God ſeems in all times of his Meſſengers to be ſo abundant in giving teſtimony thereunto, that men may not onely find much in <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalms</hi> (as our Saviour (then) directed to ſearch for his firſt coming in his Kingdom of Patience,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> p. 81, 82, 83 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his ſecond coming and Kingdom of Power then to be ſet up in the World) they may have abundant evidence beſides, from his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Evangeliſts, and many ſorts of perſons, there recorded, to have been divinely inſpired; and, after all, our Saviour's moſt ſure Explications and Applications of all the former ſtrongly aſſerted, and ſent by his beloved Diſciple St. <hi>John,</hi> unto the Churches for their Edification and Comfort, unto his ſaid Coming again, as all along by the quotations in the ſaid two Books (by his remarkable hand ſent abroad of late) may more fully appear to ſuch as duly weigh the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But it may be alledged againſt theſe things, as it was at our Saviours firſt coming, <hi>Have any of the Rulers believed on him?</hi> So, <hi>Do the Great, and Learned, or Eminent Men in the World, of many Ages paſt, acknowledge theſe things?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was a great ſtumbling-block to many ſorts of the People of the Jews, that their Rulers did not; But were they not both by our Saviour (therefore) characterized by <hi>Blind leaders of the blind, &amp;c.</hi> and the ſame obſtacle hath many times ſince, and ſtill is, like to fall in the way of many. But the Scripture informs men on the other hand, <hi>Not many Wiſe, not many Learned, not many Noble, &amp;c.</hi> though ſome of all thoſe, &amp;c. So neither are theſe Truths without ſome Witneſſes of all ſuch ranks; and many in the pureſt primitive times, beſides more late ones (as hath been abundantly not long ſince publiſhed) but while men (as we hinted before) have more reſpect to Men, than God's Word, it is no wonder they are in ſome great matters miſled: Therefore (in a word) they are to be warned that they pin not their faith on other mens ſleeves, but with the <hi>Noble Bereans</hi> ſearch by the holy Scriptures, whether theſe things be ſo, if they would ſtand upon a ſure foundation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It matters not to thee (ſaithful Chriſtian) who are the perſons that plead for or againſt any divine Truth, whilſt thou mayeſt find the Word of God evidently to give witneſs to it; and if in this thou follow any ſort of men rather than Chriſts truth, thou wilt certainly be miſled above what thou mighteſt in other things; for our Saviour hath in theſe things forewarned thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8. Their Faith will be wanting when he cometh, as in the latter part of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106268:25"/>Chapter is particularly deſcribed; wherefore they ſhould pray and not faint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But there is one dangerous ſhifting here comes on to be avoided.</hi> i.e. <hi>Many good men, able, faithful and well approved, do not at all own ſuch Doctrines, and ſome reckon them to be little better than fancies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No good men, however qualified or approved in this world, are perfect. Who better, or equal to the Apoſtles of Chriſt? yet the chiefeſt of them ſhewed their infirmities. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were ſo at difference, that they parted from each other; and <hi>Barnabas</hi> was far carried away with the diſſimulation of a miſtaken party; and there was much adoe among ſome of them, before the believing Gentiles could be received, though the Word and Will of God was for it, till God made the buſineſs out of queſtion (but the evidence of the <hi>Jews</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, and things contemporary with them, have much more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that they ſhall be accompliſhed: and though good men in many things have been upheld in upright wayes, pleaſing unto God, yet they may fail in others; and what ſorts of good men have not had their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? and is not that vanity in many able, approved and learned men, that they are apt ſo to conceive of their light, or parts, or learning, or experience, that nothing is to be owned and received, that is not ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their own ſtandard? and all is but fancy that is not comprized within the ſummary of their Faith, although they have not ſearched and tryed them by the true touch-ſtone of the Word? But let all ſuch, be they who they will, either in their own eſteem, or in the eſteem of others, take heed of being in ſuch regard reſiſters of any divine Truth. God hath more Truths yet to reveal, than any times paſt have been hitherto capable of receiving, or that theſe times we are in can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to; but will be revealed and received too, at the time when his Temple ſhall be opened in Heaven; and when men ſhall ſee in his Temple the Ark of his Teſtament, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. But he hath now in our times revealed ſome things which he would have owned by us, which have not of many years paſt been ſo manifeſt and clear, but are now very ſeaſonable to be many ways improved in theſe laſt days.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But the Teachers of ſuch or ſuch Doctrines have many of them had ſuch faylings, or given ſuch offence, as occaſion others to ſtumble, or they are ſo mean in eſteem as not much to be regarded,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though perhaps ſome have been ſuch, yet not all: there are very ancient as well as modern Witneſſes thereof, and in moſt times ſome, and good and eminent men too, as well as meaner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, if men would impartially enquire; and much I doubt not might be fairly anſwered to particular exceptions (if things were duely
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106268:25"/>weighed, but it hath been uſual to take up any vain pretences againſt what is really good; but the rule of old was <hi>non quis, ſed quid.</hi> Our Saviour hath two cautions in hearing; <hi>take heed what,</hi> and <hi>take heed how;</hi> but he reſerveth to himſelf liberty to ſend his meſſages by any ſort of men: As we muſt not have his <hi>Faith with reſpect of perſons;</hi> ſo not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive or own it in reſpect of perſons, but as founded upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Truth. How oft hath the looking aſquint upon Gods Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, upon ſome appearing or pretended occaſion of diſreſpect or other, proved a ſad judgement unto many to whom they have come, and who have been ſent by him in great turnings of times, that have not been aſſaulted in ſome kind, reſpecting their perſons? Thoſe rebels of old excited one another to ſmite the Prophet with the tongue, that they might not give heed to any of his words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.18. However, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the worſt that can be pretended againſt mens perſons, men may conſider, that Gold that is found but in dunghills ordraughts, if by the touch-ſtone it be approved to be Gold, deſerveth to be laid up (when waſhed from the ſoil upon it) as well as that which had been kept cloſely before, in the Treaſury or Cabinet. <hi>Wiſdom will be juſtified of her Children,</hi> in all her Oracles, for this reaſon, <hi>becauſe they are her Oracles.</hi> Gods Servants here are to have their grain of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance; but the vain World uſeth to preoccupate the judgment of the Saints unjuſtly by harſh cenſures and hard ſpeeches, as Antichriſt hath done their reign to come by wicked Idolatry.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But theſe Doctrines,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhake the foundation of worldly intereſt and enjoyments: for if Chriſts glorious appearance will be ſo terrible, and work ſuch deſolations and changes, and that its approach is nigh, what will become of Poſſeſſors treaſures and their owners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Good to the good, and evil to the evil, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and therefore God ſeems to cauſe ſuch ſeaſonable Truths to be known and publiſhed in theſe laſt dayes, to looſen mens hearts from the world, and eſpecially from their wickedneſs, and as <hi>Daniel</hi> counſelled <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi> when he was to be driven from his moſt ſtately Palace to feed among the Beaſts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Let men break off their ſins by righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and their iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> Gods poor) <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and like to our Saviours wiſe Steward, let them make themſelves friends with the Mammon of iniquity, whileſt time ſerveth, that they may receive them into their houſes, when they are out of their ſteward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips; even thoſe houſes and manſions which our <hi>Saviour went to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for his little little flock in his Kingdom;</hi> and at his return will give them poſſeſſion of them with himſelf.</p>
            <p>But here to be ſhort: Let ſober and ſerious Chriſtians further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106268:26"/>that God hath not ſaid ſo very much of theſe things in his Word to no purpoſe, but every truth contained in his Word is uſeful in its ſeaſon to his Church, working (as all holy Scriptures do) Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in his People: beſides take notice, that myſtical Truths may now from the Word be expected to be revealed in great meaſure, when that point of time is haſtening to us, wherein the Myſtery of God will be finiſhed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. And according to <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. which Text many ſtumble at. Chriſt ſaith, (that as man) <hi>he knew not the day and hour of the laſt times</hi> (at leaſt not ſtrictly taken) yet even then, he being ſuch a perſon <hi>in whom the Godhead dwelled bodily,</hi> as <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9. did then to his Diſciples make known much of theſe things, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>Luke</hi> 20, &amp; 21. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13. and in other places (at leaſt in ſome latitude) although in a ſtrict ſenſe the day and hour of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming may not be known to us, by means of incompleat or broken years, or ſome imperfection of Chronology, or the like, as God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to over-rule, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So likewiſe when Chriſt tells his Diſciples, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5, 6. <hi>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons</hi> (then in the ſtate they were in at preſent) <hi>which the Father hath put in his own power.</hi> Yet even then he tells them in the next <hi>verſ. of being endued with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from on high,</hi> on <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> then near at hand; when they were not only fitted for the work of the Miniſtry, and to work Miracles, but to know the great Myſteries of holy Scriptures, and of <hi>Daniel</hi> in particular; as was ſeen in <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. in <hi>James, Acts</hi> 15.15, 16, 17. In St. <hi>Paul</hi> abundantly, in his Epiſtles, and even in <hi>Jude's</hi> ſhort Epiſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. But above all, the beloved Diſciple, St. <hi>John,</hi> is taught to unlock all the formerly ſhut up Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the greatly beloved Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> even to thoſe times, and that by Chriſt himſelf, in the whole Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward to be uſeful for his Churches ſucceſſively, for the time of the end, for which they were reſerved (as is obſervable, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.17, 19. <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.40. &amp; 12.4, 9. So that from that time they were unſealed by our Saviour and his holy Spirit, who through all times of the Seals, hath hitherto opened his Myſteries in their orders, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> much of this nature might be added, not only to remove the frivolous, and erroneous conceits of many reſpecting theſe things, whileſt they little conſider in what Glory and Majeſty Chriſt will then come in the Clouds of Heaven, or with Clouds, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. accompanied with all his holy Angels. And as <hi>Enoch</hi> long ſince propheſied, <hi>Jude</hi> 14. <hi>with ten thouſands of his Saints, who ſhall then come with him,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 1. <hi>ult.</hi> and 4.14. that he then uniting their Spirits to their Bodies, may make them alive and remain againſt his laſt coming (as <hi>verſes</hi> 15,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106268:26"/>17.) and may ſo make them capable to behold his glory in the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> the thouſand years, <hi>John</hi> 17.4. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>In ſum then (Chriſtian) take notice of theſe repreſentations of the points of Doctrine, reſpecting Chriſts comings and Kingdom on earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Theſe Points, as all other divine Truths, are Uniform,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See this conſidered in many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in Obſer.</hi> 31.</note> and bear an excellent harmony with themſelves, and all other true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and no wayes twharting or diſagreeing in themſelves, or with any others, which ſound Chriſtians own or profeſs, as by comparing particulars will appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is nothing new in them in ſubſtance, being only fuller explications of divine Myſteries, before more darkly couched, yet contained in the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They will more and more be manifeſt to have no greater enemies than ignorance of Gods Divine Counſels revealed, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unbelief or prophaneneſs, being of themſelves ſacred and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truths; which likewiſe is another evidence of their divine excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> That now they are in their due ſeaſon eſpecially made known by the eſpecial grace of God, to be publiſhed to and improved by his faithful People upon whom the ends of the World are coming.</p>
            <p>And as for ſome miſapprehenſions of ſome good men to whom My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of this nature are not yet diſcovered; whence not only a ſtrange ſlighting of theſe great things of God ſometimes proceeds; but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hard ſpeeches both concerning the things, and Chriſts own wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of them according to his Word, who are therein to be pittied and prayed for with endeavours of information, if God afford oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, and ſhall be pleaſed to vouchſafe his bleſſing: However all men herein are to be admoniſhed, that they offend not any ſuch wayes againſt Chriſt more than they are aware of, by contemning or ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil of thoſe divine matters they underſtand not, and therefore do not believe, yet will be fulfilled in their ſeaſon. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata's formerly omitted, though ſmaller faults be paſſed by.</head>
            <p>IN the Forrunner. pag. 10. before line 26. add <hi>[of the eternal decrees]</hi> p. 34. r. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. in the marg. In <hi>Irenicon,</hi> p. <hi>ult.</hi> Chron. Table, l. 18. r. 410. In the Preface, p. 3. l. 1. r. <hi>witneſſings.</hi> In the Advertiſement, l. 19. 1. <hi>ſupernal.</hi> p. 84. l. 27. r. <hi>Phariſees, not Diſciples.</hi> p. 100. l. 26. 1. <hi>Ideom.</hi> p. 101. l. 39. r. <hi>ſpecial, not ſpiritual.</hi> p. 109. l. 6. r. <hi>thy.</hi> In Parallel. p. 36. l. 9. r. <hi>incheate.</hi> Plain Diſcovery, p. 1. l. 4. r. <hi>new.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
